<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Here begynneth the compost of Ptholomeus, prynce of astronomye: translated oute of Frenche in to Englysshe, for them that wolde haue knowlege of the compost</title>
            <title>Compost et kalendrier des bergiers. English. Selections.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1530</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 170 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 69 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10201</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20480</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S115325</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99850544</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99850544</idno>
            <idno type="VID">15753</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10201)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 15753)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 140:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Here begynneth the compost of Ptholomeus, prynce of astronomye: translated oute of Frenche in to Englysshe, for them that wolde haue knowlege of the compost</title>
                  <title>Compost et kalendrier des bergiers. English. Selections.</title>
                  <author>Ptolemy, 2nd cent. Tetrabiblos.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[136] p. : ill. (woodcuts)  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Imprynted by me Robert Wyer, dwellynge at the sygne of seynt Iohn Euangelyste, in seynt Martyns Parysshe in the Felde, in the bysshop of Norwytche rentes, besyde Charyng crosse,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1530?]]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation of selections from "Le compost et kalendrier des bergiers", chiefly drawn from the "Tetrabiblos" of Ptolemy.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name and address from colophon; publication date conjectured by STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: a-r⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Astronomy, Greek --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Astrology --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:15753:1"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:15753:1"/> Here begynneth The Compoſt of Ptholomeus / Prynce of Aſtronomye: Tran<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſlated oute of Frenche in to Englyſſhe / for them that wolde haue knowlege of the Compoſt.</p>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>Ptholomeus.</head>
                  <figDesc>Ptholomeus (or Claudius Ptolemy), in king's clothes, and a lady look on astrological instruments: a globe and an astrolabe quadrant</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <pb facs="tcp:15753:2"/>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>royal English blazon or coat of arms</figDesc>
                  <q>DIEV ET MON DROIT</q>
                  <q>HONI SOIT QVI MAL Y PENSE</q>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:15753:2"/>
            <head>¶ Here begynneth the Table of this preſent boke.</head>
            <p>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <label>FIrſte</label> the prologue of Ptholomeus.</item>
                  <item>
                     <label>¶ Another prologue of .ii. other Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nomyers / that ſheweth &amp; proueth the Auctours Prologue true that is before.</label>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <label>¶ Here foloweth to ſhewe howe man chaun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>geth
.xii. tymes / as the .xii. monthes dothe.</label>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <label>¶ Here foloweth to knowe the .xii. ſygnes in theyr courſe reygnynge / and rulynge vpon the .xii. partyes of mannes body / and whiche ben good for lettynge of blode / &amp; indifferent / or euyll.</label> Capitulo .Primo.</item>
                  <item>
                     <label>¶ Hereafter foloweth the Nature of the .xii. ſygnes.</label> Capitulo .ſecundo.</item>
                  <item>
                     <label>¶ The Nothomye of the bones in ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dy / and the nombre of them / whiche is in all .CC. and .xl viii.</label> Capitulo
.iii.</item>
                  <item>
                     <label>¶ The Flubothomye / with the names of the vaynes / and where they reſte / and how they ought to be letten blode.</label> Capitulo .iiii.</item>
                  <item>
                     <label>¶ To knowe whan a man is hole / or diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to ſyckenes.</label> Capitulo .iiii.</item>
                  <item>
                     <label>¶ The ſygne to knowe a man hole / &amp; well diſpoſed in his body.</label> Capitulo .v.</item>
                  <item>
                     <label>¶ Of ſygnes contrary to them aforeſayd / by the whiche Ptholomeus knewe whan he or other were ſycke.</label> Capitulo
.vi.</item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:15753:3"/>
                  <item>
                     <label>¶ Other ſygnes almoſte ſemblable to them aforeſayd / and ſheweth the replection of euyl humours / &amp; for to be purged of them.</label> Ca. vii.</item>
                  <item>
                     <label>¶ A deuyſyon &amp; regyment of tyme / the whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che Ptholomeus vſed / after that the ſeaſon and tyme requyred.</label> Capitulo .viii.</item>
                  <item>
                     <label>¶ The regyment for Prymetyme / that is for to ſaye Marche / Apryll / &amp; May.</label> Cap<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> .ix.</item>
                  <item>
                     <label>¶ The regyme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t for the tyme of Somer / that is Iune
/ Iuly / and Auguſt.</label> Cap<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> .x.</item>
                  <item>
                     <label>¶ The regyment for Harueſt / is Septembre Octobre
/ and Nouembre.</label> Cap<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> .xi.</item>
                  <item>
                     <label>¶ The regyme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t for wynter tyme / is Decem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ber / Ianuary / and February.</label> Cap<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> .xii.</item>
                  <item>
                     <label>¶ Here after foloweth the .iiii. Elementꝭ: and the .iiii. Complections of man.</label> Cap<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> .xiii.</item>
                  <item>
                     <label>¶ And alſo after foloweth the Aſtrologye of Ptholomeus.</label> Capitulo .xiiii.</item>
                  <item>
                     <label>¶ Howe Ptholomeus ſheweth more playn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of the foure Clementes / and of the ſymyly<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tude of the erth / and howe that euery Planet is one aboue another / and ſheweth whiche of them ben maſculyne / as theſe .v. Saturne / Iupiter / Mars / Sol / and Mercury. And of .ii. femenyne
/ as Venus / and Luna / and whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che of them is northly / &amp; ſouthly / and whiche ben oryentall / or occydentall.</label> Cap<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> .xv.</item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:15753:3"/>
                  <item>
                     <label>¶ Of the equynoccyall &amp; zodyacke / that ben in the .ix. ſkyes / that contayneth the Fyrma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment vnder it.</label> Capitulo
.xvi.</item>
                  <item>
                     <label>¶ Hereafter foloweth a very ſubtyll varya<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyon in the ſkye.</label> Capitulo .xvii.</item>
                  <item>
                     <label>¶ Of .ii. great Cyrcles / that is to ſay one me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rydien / and the other ozyron that interſequeth one the other / &amp; croſſeth dyrectly.</label> Ca. xviii.</item>
                  <item>
                     <label>¶ Alſo hereafter do folowe two other great Cyrcles of the ſkye / &amp; foure ſmall.</label> Ca. xix.</item>
                  <item>
                     <label>¶ Of the ryſynge and reſconſynge of the ſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnes in the ozyron.</label> Capitulo .xx.</item>
                  <item>
                     <label>¶ Of the deuyſyons of the erthe / and of the regyons.</label> Capitulo .xxi.</item>
                  <item>
                     <label>¶ Of the varyacyon that is for dyuers haby<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tacions &amp; regyons of the erth.</label> Cap<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> .xxii.</item>
                  <item>
                     <label>¶ Of the deuyſyon of the erthe / and onely of the parte enhabyted.</label> Capitulo .xxiii.</item>
                  <item>
                     <label>¶ The great and meruaylous conſyderacy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and great vnderſtandynge of the Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nomyers &amp; Aſtrologyens.</label> Cap<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> .xxiiii.</item>
                  <item>
                     <label>¶ Of the Pomell of the ſkyes a ſterre called the ſterre of the Northe / nere the whiche is the pole artyke called ſeptemtryonall.</label> Ca. xxv.</item>
                  <item>
                     <label>¶ Of Andromeda a ſterre fyxed.</label> Ca. xxvi.</item>
                  <item>
                     <label>¶ Of Perſeus a ſterre fyxed / Lorde of the ſpere.</label> Capitulo .xxvii.</item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:15753:4"/>
                  <item>
                     <label>¶ Of Ozyron a ſterre fyxed / and the fela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes.</label> Capitulo .xxviii.</item>
                  <item>
                     <label>¶ Of Alhabor a ſterre fyxed.</label> Cap<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
.xxix.</item>
                  <item>
                     <label>¶ Of the Lyons herte / a ſterre fyxed.</label> Capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulo .xxx.</item>
                  <item>
                     <label>¶ Of the ſterre fyxed called Nebuluſe / &amp; of another called the golden Cuppe.</label> Ca. xxx.</item>
                  <item>
                     <label>¶ Of the Porke eſpyke / a ſterre fyxed.</label> Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitulo .xxxii.</item>
                  <item>
                     <label>¶ Of the Crowne ſeptemtryonall / a ſterre fyxed.</label> Capitulo .xxxiii.</item>
                  <item>
                     <label>¶ And of the Scorpions herte: a ſterre fyxed.</label> Capitulo .xxxiiii.</item>
                  <item>
                     <label>¶ Of the flyinge Egle / a ſterre fyxed.</label> Capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulo .xxxv.</item>
                  <item>
                     <label>¶ And of the Fyſſhe merydyonall / a ſterre fyxed.</label> Capitulo .xxxvi.</item>
                  <item>
                     <label>¶ Of Pegaſus that ſygnyfieth the Horſe of honoure a ſterre fyxed.</label> Cap<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> .xxxvii.</item>
                  <item>
                     <label>¶ Of the deuyſyon of the twelue houſes / as well in the erthe / as in the heuens / as it dothe appere.</label> Capitlo
.xxxviii.</item>
                  <item>
                     <label>¶ How the Planettes reygne in euery houre of the daye and the nyght.</label> Cap<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> .xxxix.</item>
                  <item>
                     <label>¶ Alſo of the Natures of the .vii. Planettes: with theyr dyſpoſycions / after the ſayinge of Ptholomeus / prynce of Aſtronomye.</label> Ca. xl.</item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:15753:4"/>
                  <item>
                     <label>¶ And foloweth / to knowe the Fortunes &amp; deſtenyes of man and woman borne vnder the .xii. Sygnes (after the ſayinge of Ptholo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meus) prynce of Aſtronomye.</label> Cap<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> .xli.</item>
                  <item>
                     <label>¶ The prologue of Ptholomeus vpon the .xii. ſygnes.</label> Capitulo .xlii.</item>
                  <item>
                     <label>¶ And after foloweth the Scyence of Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zonomye / for to knowe the naturall inclyna<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyon of man and woman.</label> Capitulo
.xliii.</item>
                  <item>
                     <label>¶ And of the Iugementes of mannes body.</label> Capitulo .xliiii.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <trailer>¶ Finis.</trailer>
            <trailer>¶ Thus endeth the Table of the Compoſt of Ptholomeus.</trailer>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg> 
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="prologue">
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:15753:5"/>
               <figure>
                  <head>Ptholomeus.</head>
                  <figDesc>two illustrations of Ptholomeus (or Claudius Ptolemy) with an astrolabe</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="Ptolomy" type="prologue">
            <pb facs="tcp:15753:5"/>
            <head>¶ The prologue of Ptholomeus.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>O as we vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de Ptholomeus ſaythe / that lyuynge and dyeng is all at the pleaſure of almygh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ty god. Yet he ſayth that a man may lyue by the cour<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe of nature .lxxii. yere or more. And he ſayth alſo as moche tyme / as a man hath to growe in beaute / length / bredthe / and ſtrengthe. So moche tyme hathe he to waxe olde and feble to his ende. But the terme to growe in beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te / hyghte / and ſtrength / is .xxxvi. yere. And the terme to waxe olde / feble / and weyke / to tourne to the erthwarde / whiche is in all to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyther .lxxii. yere / that he ought to lyue after the courſe of nature. And they that dye before this tyme / often it is by the vyolence and out rage done to theyr Complexion and nature. But they that lyue aboue this terme / it is by good regyment &amp; enſygnementꝭ / after whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che a man hathe gouerned hymſelfe. To this purpoſe of lyuynge and dyeng: Ptholomeus ſayth / that the thynge that we deſyre moſte in this worlde is to lyue longe: And the thynge that we moſte fere is to dye ſoon. ¶ Thus he trauayled his vnderſtandyng / &amp; made great
<pb facs="tcp:15753:6"/> dylygence to knowe and to do thyngꝭ poſſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble &amp; requyſyte for to lyue longe / hole / &amp; ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully / whiche this preſent Compoſt ſheweth &amp; techeth. wherefore we wyll ſhewe you of the bodyes Celeſtyall / &amp; of theyr nature &amp; mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uynges: &amp; this p<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſent boke is named the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſt of Ptholomeus / for it co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>prechendeth ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly all the Compoſt. And this preſent boke is made for them that be of ſmall lernynge / to brynge them to great vnderſtandyng. Thus Ptholomeus ſayd alſo that the deſyre to lyue longe was in his ſoule / the whiche alwaye laſteth / wherfore he wold that his deſyre we<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re accomplyſſhed after his deth / as before. He ſayde ſyth the foule dyeth nat / and in it is the deſyre to lyue longe / it ſhuld be an infallable payne (nat to lyue after deth: as before) for he that lyueth nat after his corporall deth / ſhall nat haue that / that he hathe deſyred (that is to wete) to lyue longe
/ &amp; ſhuld abyde in eternal payne / if his deſyre were nat accomplyſſhed. So concluded the ſayd Ptholomeus neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry thynges for hym and other / to knowe and to do that whiche appertayned / to lyue after deth as before. And truthe it is that he that ly<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ueth / but the lyfe of this worlde onely / and thoughe he lyued an .C. yere / yet he lyued nat properly longe. But he ſhuld lyue longe that
<pb facs="tcp:15753:6"/> at the ende of this preſent lyfe / ſhulde begyn the lyfe eternall (that is to ſaye) the lyfe euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſtynge in heuen. So a man oughte to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme his lyfe in this worlde corporally / that they may lyue ſpiritually without ende. For as he ſayd / one ſhal lyue euerlaſtyngly with out dyenge / and whan he hathe the pardura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble lyfe he ſhall be parfyte. And alſo by this poynt and none otherwyſe ſhalbe accomplyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed the deſyre of longe lyuynge in this worl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de. The foreſayd Ptholomeus alſo knowle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged / that the lyfe of this worlde was ſoone paſte and gone. wherfore this Ptholomeus thought that .lxxii. yeres / here in this vale of wretched myſery / is but a lytell and a ſmall terme of lyfe / to the lyfe euerlaſtyng: the whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che neuer ſhal haue endynge. And therfore he ſaythe
/ he that offeryth hym ſelfe here to lyue vertuouſly in this worlde / after this lyfe he ſhall receyue the ſwete lyue / that is ſure and laſteth euer without ende. For though a man lyued here a .C. yere and more: it is but a lytell terme to the lyfe to come. Therfore ſayth this Ptholomeus / I wyl lyue ſoberly with theſe ſmall temporal goodes that Iheſu hath lende me: and euer to exyle the deſyre of worldly ry<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ches and worldly worſhyp. For they that la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour for it: &amp; haue loue to theyr goodꝭ &amp; vayne
<pb facs="tcp:15753:7"/> worſhyppes / ofte it departeth mary from he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly treaſoure. It ſhytteth ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes herte that god may nat entre. And buyldeth man a pla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce of no reſt in the lowe lande of derkeneſſe</p>
         </div>
         <div n="supporting Ptolomy" type="prologue">
            <head>¶ Here after foloweth another Prologue of two other Aſtronomyers / that ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth &amp; proueth the auctours Prolo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gue true that is before reherſed.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>E it to vnderſtande / that there be in the yere .iiii. quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters / the whiche be named thus. Vere / Hyems / Eſtas / and Autumnus. Theſe be the .iiii. ſeaſons in the yere / as Pryme tyme is the ſprynge of the yere / as Feueryere / Marche / and Apryll. In theſe .iii. monthes euery grene thynge growynge / be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gynneth to budde and flouryſſhe. ¶ Than co<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>meth ſomer as Maye / Iune / and Iuly / and theſe .iii. monthes / euery herbe / grayne / &amp; tree / is in his kynde and in his moſte ſtrength and beautye / &amp; than the Sonne is at the hygheſt. ¶ Than cometh Autumne: as Auguſt / Sep<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tembre / and Octobre / that all theſe fruytes waxen type / and ben gatheryd and howſed. ¶ Than cometh Nouembre
/ Decembre / and
<pb facs="tcp:15753:7"/> Ianyuere / &amp; theſe .iii. monthes be in the wyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter / that tyme the Son<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e is at the loweſt / and is the tyme of lytel profyte. As we Aſtrono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myers ſay / that the age of man is .lxxii. yere / &amp; that we lyken but to one hole yere / for euer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>more we take .vi. yere for euery Monthe / as Ianyuere / or Feueryere / and ſo forthe / for as the yere chaungeth by the .xii. monthes: In to .xii. dyuers maners / ſo dothe a man chaunge hym ſelfe .xii. tymes in his lyfe / by .xii. aeges / and euery aege laſteth .vi. yere / if ſo be that he lyue to .lxxii. for .iii. tymes .vi. maketh .xviii. and .vi. tymes .vi. maketh .xxxvi. And than man is at the beſt
/ and alſo at the hygheſt / &amp; .xii. tymes .vi. maketh .lxxii. And that is the aege of man.</p>
            <p>¶ Thus muſte you counte and reken for eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry monthe .vi. yere / or ellys it may be vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtande by the .iiii. quarters and ſeaſons of the yere. So man is deuyded in to .iiii. partyes: as to youthe / ſtrengthe
/ wyſdome / and aege. He ſo to be .xviii. yere yonge .xviii. yere ſtronge xviii. yere in wyſedome / &amp; the fourthe .xviii. yere to go to the full of the aege of .lxxii.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="introduction">
            <head>¶ Here foloweth to ſhewe howe man chaungeth .xii. tymes
/ euen as the .xii. monthes dothe.</head>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:15753:8"/> 
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>E muſte take the firſte .vi. yere for Ianyuere / the whiche is of no vertue nor ſtrength / in that ſeaſon noo thynge on the erthe groweth. So man after that he is borne / tylhe be .vi. yere of aege is with lytell or no wytte / ſtrengthe / or cunnynge / and maye do lytell or no thynge that cometh to profyte.</p>
            <p>¶ Than cometh Feueryere: and than the day<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>es longeth / &amp; the Sonne is more hotter / than the feldes begyn to wax grene. So the other
.vi. yere tyll he come to .xii. the childe begyn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>eth to growe bygger / and is apte to lerne ſuche thynges as is taughte hym.</p>
            <p>¶ Than cometh the monthe of Marche / In whiche the labourer ſoweth the erth / &amp; plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth trees / and edyfyeth houſes / the childe in theſe .vi. yeres waxeth bygge to lerne doctry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne and ſcycnce / and to be fayre and pleſaunt &amp; louynge / for than he is .xviii. yere of aege.</p>
            <p>¶ Than cometh Apryll / that the erthe &amp; the trees is coueryd with grene floutes. And in euery partye goodes encreaſeth habundaunt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. Than cometh the yonge man to gather the ſwete floures of hardynes / but than beware that the colde wyndes and ſtormes of vyces bete nat downe the floures of good maners / 
<pb facs="tcp:15753:8"/> that ſhulde brynge man to honoure / for than is he
.xxiiii. yere of aege.</p>
            <p>¶ Than cometh Maye / that is bothe fayre &amp; pleſaunte / for than byrdes ſynge in woddes and foreſtes nyght and daye / the Sonne ſhy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth hote / as than man is moſte luſty / mygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty / and of delyuer ſtrengthe / &amp; ſeketh playes / ſportes / and manly paſtymes / for than is he full .xxx. yere of aege.</p>
            <p>¶ Than cometh Iune: and than is the ſonne at the hygheſt in his merydyonall / he may aſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cende no hygher in his ſtacion. His glemeryn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge golden beames typeth the corne / and than man is .xxxvi. yere / he may aſcende no more For than nature hathe gyuen hym courage &amp; ſtrengthe at the full / and typeth the ſedes of parfyte vnderſtandynge.</p>
            <p>¶ Than cometh Iuly: that our fruytes be ſet on ſonnynge / &amp; our corne a hardenynge / but than the Sonne begynneth a lytell for to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcende do wnewarde. So than man goth fro youthe to warde aege / and begynneth for to acquaynt hym with ſadnes: for than he is co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me to .xlii. yere.</p>
            <p>¶ After that than cometh Auguſt / than we gather in our corne / and alſo the fruytꝭ of the erthe. And than man dothe his dylygence to gather for to fynde hym ſelf to maynteyn his
<pb facs="tcp:15753:9"/> wyfe / children / and his houſholde whan age cometh on hym. And than after that .vi. yere / he is .xlviii. yere of aege.</p>
            <p>¶ Than cometh Septembre / that wynes be made / and the fruytꝭ of the trees be gatheryd. And than there withall he dothe freſſhely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyn to garnyſſhe his houſe / and make prouy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſion of nedefull thynges / for to lyue with in wynter / whiche draweth very nere / &amp; than man is in his moſte ſtedfaſt &amp; couetous eſtate proſperous in wyſedome / purpoſynge to ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and kepe / aſmoche as ſhuld be ſufficyent for hym in his aege / whan he may gather no more. And than is he .liiii. yere of aege.</p>
            <p>¶ And than cometh Octobre: that all is in to the forſayd houſe gaderyd / bothe corne &amp; alſo other maner of fruytes. And alſo the labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers plowe and ſowe newe ſedes on the erth: for the yere to come. And than he that nought ſoweth nought gatheryth. And than in theſe vi. yere a man ſhall take hym ſelfe vnto god for to do penaunce and good werkes / &amp; than the benefytes the yere after his dethe / he maye gather / and haue ſpirituall profyte / and than man is fully the terme of .lx. yeres.</p>
            <p>¶ Than cometh nouembre / that the dayes be very ſhorte / and the Sonne in maner gyueth but lytel hete / and the trees loſen theyr leuys.
<pb facs="tcp:15753:9"/> The feldes that were grene loketh hoore and graye / Than all maner of herbes ben hydde in the grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de / and than apperyth no floures. And than wynter is come / that the man hath vnderſtandynge of aege / and hathe loſte his kyndely hete and ſtrength. His teth begyn to rot / and to fayle hym. And than hath he lytel hope of longe lyfe / but defyreth to come to the lyfe euerlaſtynge. And theſe .vi. yeres make hym .lxvi. of aege.</p>
            <p>¶ Than laſt cometh Decembre / full of colde with froſte and ſnowe / with great wyndes and ſtormy wethers / that a man may nat la<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bour nor nought do. The ſonne is than at the loweſt that it maye diſcende. That the trees &amp; the erthe be hydde in ſnowe / than it is good to holde them nygh the fyre / and to ſpende the goodes that they gat in ſomer. For than man begynneth to waxe croked &amp; feble / couchyng and ſpyttynge / and loothſom / and than he lo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſeth his parfyte vnderſtandyng / and his hey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res deſyre his deth. And theſe .vi. yere maketh hym full .lxxii. yeres. And if he lyue any lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger / it is by his good guydynge / and dyetyng in his youth. Howe be it / it is poſſyble that a man may lyue tyll he be a .C. yere of aege: but there be but fewe that lyueth ſo lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge tyll they come to a .C. yere of aege.
<pb facs="tcp:15753:10"/> ¶ wherfore Ptholomeus ſaythe moreouer / that of lyuynge or dyeng / the heuenly bodyes may ſtere a man both to good &amp; euyll / with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out doubte it is ſo. But yet maye man with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtande it by his owne fre wyl / to do what he wyll hym ſelf / good or badde euermore. And aboue the whiche inclynacion is the myght &amp; wyll of god / that longeth the lyfe of man by his goodnes / or to make it ſhort by iuſtyce.</p>
            <p>¶ wherfore I wyl ſhewe you of the bodyes Celeſtyall / and of theyr nature and mouyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges / And this preſent Boke hath to name the Compoft of Ptholomeus / for it comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth fully all the compoft / as dayes
/ houres / and of the ſonne &amp; moone / &amp; of the Sygnes that the moone is in eueryday. And this boke was made for them that be lytell or no cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes / to brynge them to more vnderſtandyng and lerenynge of many dyuerſe thynges that were neceſſary for them to haue knowleg of and to vere it in theyr mynde.</p>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ Here foloweth to knowe the .xii. ſygnes in theyr courſe reygnynge and rulynge vpon the .xii. parties of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes body: and whiche ben good for lettynge of blode / &amp; indifferent / or euyll. Captiulo. Primo.</head>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:15753:10"/> 
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>O it is that I do you knowlege that I ſay that a man is a lytel world by hym ſelfe: for the lykeneſſe and ſymylytudes
/ that he hath of the great worlde / whiche is the aggregacion of the .ix. ſkyes .iiii. elementꝭ / and all thynges in them conteyned. Firſte a man hath ſuche a lykenes in the firſte mobyle / that is the ſoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raygne ſkye / and pryncipall parte of all the worlde / for lyke as in this firſte mobyle the zodyake is deuyded in .xii. partyes / that ben the .xii. Sygnes. So man is deuyded in .xii. partyes / and holdeth of the ſygnes euery par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te of his ſygne. The ſygnes ben theſe / Aries / Taurus / Gemini / Cancer / Leo
/ Virgo / Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bra / Scorpio / Sagittartus / Capricornus / &amp; Piſces. Of the whiche / thre ben of the nature of fyre / that is Aries / Leo / and Sagittarius. And thre of nature of the ayre / Gemini / Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bra / and Aquarius. And thre of the nature of water / Cancer / Scorpio / and Piſces. And thre of the nature of the erth / Taurus / Virgo and Caprtcornus. The firſt is Aries that go<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uerneth the hede / &amp; the face of man. Taurus the necke and the throte bole. Gemini the ſhol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dres / the armes / and the handes. Cancer the
<pb facs="tcp:15753:11"/> breſte / ſydes / mylte / and lyghtes. Leo the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>make / the herte / and the backe. Virgo the bely and the entrayles. Libra the nauyll / the gray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes / &amp; the partyes vnder the brau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ches. Scor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pio the pryue partyes / the genytores / the blad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der: and the fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dyment. Sagittarius the thy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghes onely. Capricornus alſo the knees onely Aquarius the legges from the knees to the he les &amp; ankles. And Piſces hath the fete in his domynyon. ¶ A man ought nat to make in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyſyon nor touche with yron / the membre go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerned of any ſygne / the daye that the moone is in it / for fere of to great effuſyon of blode that myght happen / Nor in lykewyſe whan the Sonne is in it / for the great daunger and peryll that myght folowe therof.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ Hereafter foloweth the Nature of the .xii. ſygnes. Captulo .ii.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Ries is hote and drye / na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the fyre / and gouer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neth the hed &amp; face of man: and is good for bledynge / whan the moone is in it / ſaue in the partie that it go<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uerneth and ruleth.</p>
               <div n="Taurus" type="zodiac_sign">
                  <head>¶ Taurus is euyll for bledynge.</head>
                  <p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:15753:11"/> ¶ Taurus is drye and colde / nature of erthe
/ and gouerneth the necke / and the knot vnder the throte / and is euyll for bledynge.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="Gemini" type="zodiac_sign">
                  <head>¶ Gemini is euyll for bledynge.</head>
                  <p>¶ Gemini is hote and moyſte / nature of the ayre / and gouerneth the ſholdres / the armes &amp; the handes / and is euyll for bledynge.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="Cancer" type="zodiac_sign">
                  <head>¶ Cancer is indifferent for bledynge.</head>
                  <p>¶ Cancer is colde and moyſte / nature of wa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter / and gouerneth the breſt / the ſtomake / &amp;
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e mylte / and is indifferent nouther to good nor to badde for lettynge of blode.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="Leo" type="zodiac_sign">
                  <head>¶ Leo is euyll for bledynge.</head>
                  <p>¶ Leo is hote and drye / nature of fyre: and go<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uerneth the backe and the ſydes / and euyll for blode lettynge.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="Virgo" type="zodiac_sign">
                  <head>¶ Virgo is indifferent for bledynge.</head>
                  <p>¶ Virgo is colde and drye / and nature of the erthe / and gouerneth the wombe / and the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde partyes / &amp; is nouther good nor euyll for bledynge / but betwyxte bothe.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="Libra" type="zodiac_sign">
                  <head>¶ Libra is right good for bledynge.</head>
                  <p>¶ Libra is hote and moyſt / nature of the ayre and gouerneth the nauyll / the reynes / and the lowe partyes of the wombe / &amp; is very good for bledynge.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="Scorpio" type="zodiac_sign">
                  <head>¶ Scorpio is indifferent for bledynge.</head>
                  <p>¶ Scorpius is colde &amp; moyſte / nature of the
<pb facs="tcp:15753:12"/> water / and gouerneth the membres of man / and is nouther good nor badde for bledynge / but indifferent betwene bothe.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="Sagittarius" type="zodiac_sign">
                  <head>¶ Sagittarius is good for bledynge.</head>
                  <p>¶ Sagittarius is hote and drye / nature of fy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te / and gouerneth the thyghes and is good for blode ſettynge.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="Capricorn" type="zodiac_sign">
                  <head>¶ Capricornus is euyll for bledynge.</head>
                  <p>¶ Capricornus is colde and drye / nature of erthe / and gouerneth the knees / and is euyll for bledynge.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="Aquarius" type="zodiac_sign">
                  <head>¶ Aquarius is indifferent for bledyng.</head>
                  <p>¶ Aquarius is hote &amp; moyſte / nature of ayre: and gouerneth the legges / &amp; is nouther good nor euyll for bledynge.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="Pisces" type="zodiac_sign">
                  <head>¶ Piſces is indifferent for bledynge.</head>
                  <p>¶ Piſces is colde and moyſte / nature of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter / and gouerneth the fete / &amp; is nouther good nor euyll for bledynge / but indifferent.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ Here foloweth the Nothomye of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes in mannes body / and the nombre of them: whiche is in all .ii.C. and .xl.viii. Capitulo
.iii.</head>
               <p>IN the toppe of the hede is a bone that couereth the brayne / the whiche Ptho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lomeus calleth the capytall bone. In the ſkull
<pb facs="tcp:15753:12"/> ben two bones / which ben called Parietales that holdeth the brayne cloſe &amp; ſtedfaſte. And more lower in the brayne is a bone called the crowne of the hede / and on the one ſyde / &amp; on the other ben two holes / within the which is the palys or rofe bone. In the partye behynde the hede ben .iiii .lyke bones / to the whiche the chayne of the necke holdeth. In the noſe ben .it bones. The bones of the chaftꝭ aboue ben
.xi. And of the nether iawe ben .ii. Aboue the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſyte of the brayne / there is one behynde na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med collaterall. The bones of the tethe ben .xxx. eyghte before .iiii. aboue / and .iiii .vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth ſharpe edgyd for to cutte the morſelles / &amp; there is .iiii. ſharpe .ii. aboue / and .ii
.vnderneth and ben called conynes / for they ben lyke co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyes tethe. After that ben .xvi. that be as they were hamers or gryndyng tethe / for they cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we and grynde the mete the whiche is eten / &amp; there is .iiii. aboue on euery ſyde / and .iiii .vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneth: And than the .iiii. teth of ſapyence on euery ſyde of the chaftes one aboue / &amp; one vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>derneth. In the chynne from the hede downe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde ben .xxx. bones called knottes or ioyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes. In the breſt before ben .vii. bones / and on euery ſyde .xii. rybbes. By the necke bytwene the hede and the ſholdres ben .ii. bones named the ſheres / and ben the two ſholdre blades.
<pb facs="tcp:15753:13"/> From the ſholdre to the elbowe in eche arme is a bone called the adiutor. From the elbowe to the hande on euery arme / ben .ii. bones that ben called cannes. In eche hande ben .viii. bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes / aboue the palme ben .iiii. bones / whiche ben called the combe of the hande. The bones in the fyngers in eche hande ben .xv .in euery fynger thre. At the ende of the rydge ben the hoele bones / wherto ben faſtened the two bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes of the thyghes. In eche kne is a bone cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the kne plate. From the kne to the fote in eche legge ben .ii. bones / called cannes or ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry bones. In eche fote is a bone called the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle or pyn of the fote / behynde the ancle is the hele bone in eche fote / the which is the loweſt parte of a man And aboue eche fote is a bone called the holowe bone. In the plante of eche fote ben .iiii. bones. Than ben the combes of the fete in eche of the whiche ben .v. bones. The bones in the toes i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eche fote ben the nom<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bre of .xiiii. Two bones ben before the bely for to holde it ſtedfaſt with the two brau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ches Two bones ben in the hede behynde the eres called oculares. We teken nat the te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der bones of the ende of the ſholdres / nor of the ſydes / nor dyuers lytell gryſtels and ſpeldres of bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes / for they ben comprehended in the nombre beforeſayde.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:15753:13"/>
               <head>¶ Here foloweth the Flubothomye with the names of the vaynes / &amp; where they reſte / and howe they ought to be letten blode. Capitulo .iiii.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Ere I do you to wyt: that the vayne in the myddes of the forehede wold be let ten blode / for the ache and payne of the hede / and for feuers Lytargye / and for the megryme in the hede.</p>
               <p>¶ Aboute the two eres behynde is two vay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes / the whiche ben letten blode / for to gyue clere vnderſtandynge / and vertue of lyght herynge / and for thycke brethe: and for doubte of meſelry or lepry.</p>
               <p>¶ In the temple ben two vaynes called the Artyers for that they bete / whiche ben letten blode for to demynyſſhe and take awaye the great repleccion &amp; abundaunce of blode that is in the brayne / that myghte noye the hede &amp; the iyen and it is good agaynſt the gowte the megryme / and dyuers other accydentes that maye come to the hede.</p>
               <p>¶ Vnder the tongue ben two vaynes / that ben letten blode for a ſyckenes called the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quamy / and agaynſt the ſwellynge / and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtomes
<pb facs="tcp:15753:14"/> of the throte / and agaynſt the equy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nancy / by the whiche a man myght dye ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daynly / for defaute of ſuche bledynge.</p>
               <p>¶ In the necke ben two vaynes called origy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nalles / for that they haue the courſe and abu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daunce of all the blode that gouerneth the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of man / and pryncipally the hed / but they ought nat to be letten blode without the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyle of the Surgyon / &amp; this bledynge auay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth moche to the ſyckenes of Lepry / whan it cometh pryncipally of the blode.</p>
               <p>¶ The vayne of the herte taken in the arme / profyteth to take away humours or euyll blo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de / that myght hurte the chambre of the herte or the apperteynaunce / and is good for them that ſpytteth blode / and that ben ſhorte wyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded / by the whiche a man may dye ſodaynly / for defaute of ſuche bledynge.</p>
               <p>¶ The vayne of the lyuer taken in the arme aſwaygeth the great hete of the body of man and holdeth the body in helthe / and this ble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge is profytable alſo agaynſt the yelowe axes / and appoſtome of the lyuer / &amp; agaynſt the palſy wherof a man may dye / for defaute of ſuche bledynge.</p>
               <p>¶ Bytwene the maiſter fynger and the leche fynger to lette blode helpeth the dolours that cometh in the ſtomake and ſydes / as botches / 
<pb facs="tcp:15753:14"/> and appoſtomes / and dyuers other accydentꝭ that may come to thoſe places by great abun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>daunce of blode and humours.</p>
               <p>¶ In the ſydes bytwene the wombe and the brau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>che ben two vaynes / of the whiche that of the right ſyde is letten blode for the dropſy: &amp; that of the lefte ſyde for euery ſyckenes that cometh aboute the mylte / and they ſhuld ble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de after the perſons be fatte or lene
/ take good hede at foure fyngers nyghe the incyſion: and they ought nat to make ſuche bledynge with<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>out the counſayle of the Surgyon.</p>
               <p>¶ In euery fote ben thre vaynes / of the whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che thre / one is vnder the ancle of the fote na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med ſophane / the whiche is letten blode for to ſwage and put out dyuers humours / as bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches and appoſtomes that cometh aboute the graynes / and it profyteth moche to women for to cauſe theyr menſtruoſyte to diſcende / &amp; delay the emoroydes: that cometh in the ſecrete places / and other lyke.</p>
               <p>¶ Bytwene the wreſtes of the fote / and the great too is a vayne / the whiche is letten blo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de for dyuers ſyckenes and inconuenyencꝭ: as the peſtylence that taketh a perſone ſodeynly by the great ſuperabundaunce of humours / &amp; this bledynge muſte be made within a natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall day / that is to ſaye within .xxiiii. houres
<pb facs="tcp:15753:15"/> after that the ſyckeneſſe is taken of the pacy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent / and before that the feuer come on hym / &amp; this bledynge ought to be done after that cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>polence of the pacyent.</p>
               <p>¶ In the angels of the iyen ben two vaynes the whiche ben letten blode / for the rednes of the iyen / or watry / or that renneth contynual<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly / &amp; for dyuers other ſyckenes that may hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen / and come by ouer great abundance of humours and blode.</p>
               <p>¶ In the vayne of the ende of the noſe is ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de a bledynge / the whiche is good for a redde pympled face / as ben red droppes / puſtulus / ſmall ſkabbes / &amp; other infections of the herte that maye come therin by to great repleccion / and abundaunce of blode and humours / and it auayleth moche agaynſt popeled noſes / &amp; other lyke ſyckeneſſes.</p>
               <p>¶ In the mouth in the gu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mes ben foure vay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes / that is to ſaye two aboue / &amp; two byneth the whiche ben letten blode for chauſynge &amp; canker in the mouthe / and for toth ache.</p>
               <p>¶ Bytwene the lyppe &amp; the chynne is a vay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne / that is letten blode to gyue amendement to them that haue an euyll brethe.</p>
               <p>¶ In eche arme ben foure vayne / of the whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che the vayne of the hed is the hygheſt / the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conde nexte is from the herte / the thirde is of
<pb facs="tcp:15753:15"/> the lyuer / &amp; the fourth is from the mylte other<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wyſe called the lowe lyuer vayne.</p>
               <p>¶ The vayne of the hed taken in the arme / ought to blede / for to take away the great re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleccion and abundaunce of blode that maye anoye the hed / the iyen / &amp; the brayne / &amp; auay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth greatly for chaungeable hetes / and ſwel lynge of the throte / &amp; for them that haue ſwol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>len faces and red / and for dyuers other ſycke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes that may fall and come by great abun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>daunce of blode.</p>
               <p>¶ The vayne of the mylte otherwyſe called the lowe vayn ſhuld blede agaynſt feuer ter<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyens and quartaynes / and in it ought to be made a wyde and a leſſe depe wounde: than in any other vayne / for fere of wynde that it maye gather / and for a more inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uenyence for fere of a ſenowe that is vnder it / that is called the lezarde.</p>
               <p>¶ In eche hande ben thre vaynes / wherof that aboue the thombe ought to blede / to take awaye the great hete of the vyſage / &amp; for mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che thycke blode and humours that ben in the hed / and this vayne delayeth more than that of the arme.</p>
               <p>¶ Bytwene the lytell fynger and the leche fynger is lettynge of blode: that greatly auay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leth agaynſt all feuer tercyens / &amp; quartaynes
<pb facs="tcp:15753:16"/> and agaynſt flumes: and dyuers other lettyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges that cometh to the pappes / &amp; the mylte.</p>
               <p>¶ In eche thyghe is a vayne / of the whiche bledyng auayleth agaynſt doloures of the ge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nytoures / and for to put out of mannes body humours that ben in the graynes.</p>
               <p>¶ The vayne that is vnder the ancle of the fote without is named ſciat / of the which ble dynge is moche worthe agaynſt the paynes of the flankes / and for to make auoyde and yſſue dyuers humours / whiche wolde gadre in the ſayde place / and it auayleth greatly to women / for to reſtrayne theyr menſtruoſyte / whan they haue to great abundaunce.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ Thus endeth the fleubothomye / And here foloweth to knowe whan a man is hole / or diſpoſed to ſyckenes. Capitulo
.iiii.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Owe to gyue you knowlege whan that any man is hole or ſycke
/ or diſpoſed in any wy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe to ſyckenes? wherfore thre thyngꝭ there ben: by the which Ptholomeus put knowlege whan a man is hole or ſycke / or diſpoſed to ſyckenes. If he be hole / to maynteyne &amp; kepe hym. If he be ſycke to ſeke remedye to hele hym. If he be diſpoſed
<pb facs="tcp:15753:16"/> to ſyckenes / to kepe hym that he falle nat ther in. And for eche of the thre ſayde thynges / the ſayd Ptholomeus put dyuers ſygnes. Helthe properly attemperaunce / accorde / and equaly<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te of the .iiii. qualytes of man / which ben hote colde / drye / &amp; moyſte. The whiche whan they ben well tempred and egall that the one ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mount nat the other / than the body of man is hole. But whan they ben vnegal and myſſe tempred / and the one hath power one ouer an other / than a man is ſycke or diſpoſed to ſycke<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes / and they ben the qualytes that the body holdeth of the clementes that they ben made &amp; compoſed of / that is to ſaye of the fyre hete / of the water colde / of the ayre moyſte / and of the erthe drye. The whiche qualytes / whan one is diſordred from the other / than the body is ſycke. And if that one diſtroye all the other / than the body dyeth / and the ſoule departeth.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ The ſygne to knowe a man hole / and well diſpoſed in his body. Cap<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> .v.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He firſte ſygne wherby Ptholo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meus knewe a man to be hole
/ &amp; well diſpoſed in his body / was whan he eteth and drynketh wel after the conuenaunce of the hunger &amp; thyrſte
<pb facs="tcp:15753:17"/> that he hath without makynge exceſſe. And alſo whan he dygeſteth lyghtly / and whan that he hathe eten or drynken it troubleth and greuyth nat his ſtomacke. Alſo whan he fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth good ſauoure
/ &amp; good appetyte in that he eteth and drynketh. Alſo whan he is hungry and thyrſty at the houres that he ought to ete and drinke. And alſo whan he reioyſeth hym with folke. Alſo whan they playe gladly in the feldes and gardens to take the ſwete ayre and ſporte in the medowes by water ſydes. Alſo whan he eteth gladly &amp; with good ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petyte of butter / cheſe / &amp; flawnes without le<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uynge any thynge in his dyſſhe to ſende to the almeſſe houſe. Alſo whan he ſlepeth well &amp; ſuerly without rauynge or dremynge of his beſynes. Alſo whan he feleth hym lyght: and that he walketh wel. And whan he ſweteth ſoone / and that he nyſeth lytell or nothynge. Alſo whan he is nouther to fatte nor to lene. Alſo whan he hath good coloure in his face / and that his wyttes ben all wel diſpoſed for to do theyr operacion / as his iyen for to ſe / his eres to here / his noſe to ſmell. &amp;c. ¶ And I le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue of the conuenaunce of aege / the diſpoſicion of the body / &amp; alſo of tyme. Of other ſygnes I ſay no thynge: but theſe moſt ſuffyſe for the pore lay people / to know the ſygnes of helth.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:15753:17"/>
               <head>¶ Theſe ſygnes ben contrarye to them afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayd / by the whiche Ptholomeus knewe whan he or other were ſycke. Cap<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> .vi.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Irſte whanne he may nat well ete nor drynke / or that he haue none appetyte to ete at dyner &amp; ſouper / or whan he fyndeth noo ſauoure in that he eteth or drynketh / or that he is hungry and may nat ete / whan his dygeſtyon is nat good / or that it be to longe. Alſo whan he goth to chambre moderatly as he ought to do. Alſo whan he is penſyue / ſad ſory / or heuy in right ioyous or cherefull com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panyes: than ſyckenes conſtrayneth a man to be thoughtfull. Semblably whan he maye nat ſlepe nor take his reſte a ryght and at due houre with quyetnes / as is requyſyte for all helthfull perſons to haue. And alſo whan his membres ben heuy / as his hed / his legges / and armes / with other membres. And alſo whan he may nat walke eaſely and lyghtly and that he ſpueth ofte / &amp; his colour is pale or yelowe: or whan his wyttes / as his / iyen his eres / and other do nat kyndely theyr operacy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. In lykewyſe whan he may nat labour and trauayle. Alſo whan he forgetteth lyght
<pb facs="tcp:15753:18"/> ly that which of neceſſyte ought to be kept in memory / &amp; whan he ſpytteth often / or whan his noſe thrylles abou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth in ſuperfluous hu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mours. And whan he is neclyge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in his wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kes: and whan his fleſſhe is blowen or ſwol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>len in the vyſage / in his legges / or his fete / or whan his iyen ben holowe in his hed. Theſe ben the ſygnes that ſygnyfyeth a man beyng in ſyckenes / &amp; who that hath moſte of the fore<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſayd ſygnes / moſte is infecte with ſyckenes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ Other ſygnes almoſte ſemblable to them aforeſayd / and ſheweth the replection of cuyll humours / and for to be purged of them. Capitulo .vii.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Eplection is a fulnes of euyll humours / and diſpoſycion of ſyckenes after the opynyon of Ptholomeus / of the whiche re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>plection is to knowe howe to purge the ſayd humours / that they engendre no ſyckenes / and ben knowen by the ſygnes that foloweth. ¶ Firſte whan a man hathe ouer great rednes in his face / in his handes: or in his nayles / hauynge alſo his vaynes full of blode / or bledeth to moche at the noſe / or to often / or hath payne in the forehed. Alſo wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <pb facs="tcp:15753:18"/> his eres ſoundeth / and whan his iyen wate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth / or be full of gu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me / and hath his vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandynge troubled / and whan the poulx be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teth to faſte / &amp; whan the bely is longe reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te &amp; laxe
/ &amp; whan he hath the ſyght troubled / and etynge alſo without appetyte. And by all theſe &amp; other ſygnes beforeſayd one maye knowe the body euyll diſpoſed / &amp; full of cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupte humours ſuperfluous and euyll.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ A dyuyſyon &amp; regyment of tyme / the whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che Ptholomeus vſed / after that the ſeaſon and tyme requyred. Capitulo
.viii.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S for to remedy the ſycke<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſſes / &amp; infyrmytes that a man hathe / and to kepe hym from them that ben doubted to come / Ptholo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meus ſayth that the tyme / naturally chaungeth foure tymes in the yere: and ſo they deuyde the yere in foure quarters: that is Vere / Somer / Harueſt / and wynter. And in eche of theſe quarters he dyd gouerne hym as the ſeaſons requyred to his mynde / &amp; the better it was for hym. And as the ſeaſon chaungeth / ſo chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ged he his maner of lyuyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge and doynge / and ſayth that chaungynge
<pb facs="tcp:15753:19"/> of tyme without takynge good hede often en<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gendreth infyrmytes / for that one tyme beho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth nat / to vſe ſome metes that ben good in another tyme / as that vſed in wynter is nat all good in Somer / &amp; ſo of the other ſeaſons. ¶ And for to knowe the chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gynge of tyme after theſe ſayd quarters or ſeaſons / they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyder the courſe of the Sonne by the .xii. Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnes / &amp; ſay that euery of the ſayd foure quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters and ſeaſons dureth foure Monthes / and that the Sonne paſſeth by thre ſygnes: that is to wete in Pryme tyme by Piſces / Aries / &amp; Taurus / and theſe ben the monthes / Februa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry / Marche / and Apryll / that the erthe &amp; trees reioyſeth and chargeth with grene leues and flourꝭ / that is a pleaſur to beholde. In ſomer by Gemini / Cancer
/ and Leo: and the mone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes ben Maye Iune / and Iuly / that the fruy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes of the erthe groweth and rypeth. In har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſt by Virgo / Libra / and Scorpio: and the monethes ben Auguſt / Septembre / &amp; Octo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bre / that the erth &amp; trees diſchargeth the fruytꝭ and leues / and that tyme euery body felleth &amp; gaderyth the fruytes. In wynter by Sagit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarius / Capricornus / and Aquarius: and the monethes ben Nouembre / Decembre / &amp; Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuary / that the erthe and trees ben as deed &amp; vnclothed of leues / fruytes / &amp; of all greneſſe.
<pb facs="tcp:15753:19"/> After the whiche .iiii. ſeaſons / Ptholomeus deuyſen the tyme that man maye lyue in .iiii. aeges / as youth / ſtrength / and decrepyte / and lykened to the foure ſeaſons of the yere. That is to wete / youth to Pryme tyme that is hote and moyſte: and as the herbes and trees of the erthe groweth / ſo dothe man in youthe vnto .xxv. yere growe of body / in ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth beaute &amp; vygoure. Strength is lykened vnto Somer hote and drye / and the body of man is in force and vygoure / and enrypeth vnto
.xlv. yere. Aege is compared vnto the tyme of Harueſt colde and drye that man leueth of growynge and febleth / and thynketh howe to gather &amp; ſpare for fere of defaute &amp; nede that he cometh to ſtoupynge aege / and dureth to
.lvi. yeres. Decrepyte is lykened to the ſeaſon of wynter colde and moyſte by abundaunce of colde hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours &amp; defaute of naturall hete / in the whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che tyme man ſpendeth that which he had ga<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>theryd and kepte in tyme paſſed / and if he ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue ſpared no thynge / he abydeth poore and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked / as the erthe and trees / and dureth vnto lxxii. yere or more ¶ Prymetyme is hote and moyſt / nature of ayre / and complection of the ſanguyne. ¶ Somer is hote and drye / nature of fyre / &amp; complection of the coloryke. ¶ Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſt is colde and drye / nature of erthe / &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plection
<pb facs="tcp:15753:20"/> of melancoly. ¶ wynter is cold and moyſte / nature of water / complection of the flumatyke. whan complection is wel propor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyoned / it feleth it ſelfe better diſpoſed in the tyme ſemblable to it / than it doth in other ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes. But for that euery man is nat wel com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>plectioned / they ought to do as Ptholomeus dyde / that is to take Regyment to kept them ſelfe after the ſeaſons / and gouerne them by his rules and techynges / the whiche he vſed in euery quarter of the yere for to lyue the lon<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ger / wyſely / and meryly.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ The Regyme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t for Prymetyme / that is for to ſay Marche / Apryll / &amp; May. Cap<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> .ix.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N prymetyme Ptholomeus kepte hym ſelfe metely wel clothed / nat ouer colde / nor to hote / as with thyn veſtu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>res / dowbletꝭ of ſylke / and gownes metely lyght fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with lambe moſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>menly. In this tyme is very good lettynge of blode to auoyde the cuyll humours that were gatheryd in the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy the wynter tyme. If ſyckenes happen in Prymetyme it is nat of his nature / but proce<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deth of the humours gatheryd in the wyntes
<pb facs="tcp:15753:20"/> paſſed. Prymetyme is a temperat tyme to ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke medycynes for them that ben corporat and full of thycke humours / to purge them. Alſo in this tyme men oughte to ete lyght meetes / that refreſſheth as chekyns / kyddes with ver<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gyous / borage / betes / yolkes of egges in moo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne ſhyne poched / roches / perches / pykerelles / &amp; all ſcaled fyſſhe. Alſo to drynke temperate wyne / bere / or ale / ſo that they be nat to ſtron<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge nor ouer ſwete / for in this tyme all ſwete thynges ought nat to be vſed: &amp; a man ought nat to ſlepe longe in the mornynge / and nat on the daye. The Aſtronomyers haue a gene<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rall rule / or cuſtome for al ſeaſons / that auay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leth moche agaynſt all infyrmytes and ſycke<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſſes: that is nat to loſe his appetyte for etyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge / and neuer for to ete without hunger. Alſo they ſaye that all maner fleſſhe and fyſſhe is better roſted than ſoden / and if they be ſoden to broyle on a grydeyron / or on the coles / and they ben the more holſomer.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ The regyme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t for the tyme of Somer / that is Iune / Iuly / and Auguſt. Ca .x.</head>
               <p>THe Aſtronomyers in Somer ben clo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thed with lyght go wnes and ſyngle theyr ſhyrtes &amp; ſhetes / that they lye in ben lyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nen
<pb facs="tcp:15753:21"/> / for of all the clothes it is the coldeſt / they haue dowblettes of ſylke / or of canuas / and they ete lyght metes / as chekyns with vergy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ous / yonge rabetes / lectuſe / purſlayne / melo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s coucombres / peres / plu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mes / and ſuch fyſſhes as are before named. And alſo they ete of me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes that refreſſheth / alſo they ete lytell and of<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ten / they breke theyr faſte or dyne in the more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge / or euer the Son<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e aryſe / and go to ſou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>per or it diſcende / &amp; they ete of the aboueſayd metes / &amp; ſoure ſauce to gyue them an appety<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te. They ete but lytell ſalte metes / and refay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne them from ſcratchynge / they drynke many tymes freſſhe water ſoden with ſugercandy: and alſo with other refreſſynge waters / and they do it alway whan that they ben greatly thryſty / ſafe onely at dyner and at ſouper ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me / for than they drynke feble grene wyne / or ſmall ale / or ſyngle bere. And alſo they ke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe them from ouer great trauayle / or ouer for ſynge of them ſelf / for in this tyme is no thyn ge more greuous / nor contageous than chaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fynge. In this tyme &amp; ſeaſon they do eſchewe the company of women / and they bath them ofte i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> colde water to aſwage the hete of theyr bodyes enforced by laboures. Alwaye they haue with them ſugre candy / or other ſugre &amp; dradges / wherof they take lytell &amp; often / and
<pb facs="tcp:15753:21"/> euery daye in the morenynge / they force them by cowhynge and ſpyttynge to voyde fleu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes: and voyde them aboue &amp; byneth the beſt that they maye / &amp; waſſhe theyr handes with freſſhe water / theyr vyſage &amp; mouthe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ The regyment for Harueſt / is Septembre Octobre / and Nouembre. Cap<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> .xi.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>E it to vnderſtande in Har<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ueſt Aſtronomyers be clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed after the maner of pry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metyme / but theyr clothes ben a lytell warmer. And in this tyme they do their dy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lygence to purge and clenſe them / and lettyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge them blode to tempre the humours of theyr bodyes. For it is the moſte contagyous tyme of the yere / in the whiche peryllous infyrmy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes happeneth and cometh / and therfore they ete good holſome metes / as capons / hennes / yonge pegyons that begyn to flye / and dryn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke good wynes and other good and holſome drynkes / without takynge exceſſe. In this ty<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me they kepe them from etynge of fruytꝭ / for it is a daungerous ſeaſon for the axes / &amp; they ſay that he had neuer axes that neuer ete fruy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te. In this tyme they drynke no water / &amp; they
<pb facs="tcp:15753:22"/> put no parte of them in colde water / but their handes &amp; theyr faces. They kepe theyr heedes from colde in the nyght and morenynge / and ſlepe nat in the noone tyme: &amp; kepe them from ouer great trauayle: and endure nat to moche hunger nor thyrſte / but ete whan it is tyme / &amp; nat whan theyr mawes be full.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ The regyme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t for wynter tyme / is Decem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bre / Ianuary
/ and February. Cap<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> .xii.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Oreouer as Ptholomeus dyd the Aſtronomyers nowe doth in wynter clothe them in thye<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke go wnes of roughe clothe / hye ſhorne well furred with foxe furre. For it is the warmeſt furre that is and cattes / lambes / and dyuers other thycke furres that ben good &amp; holſome. In the tyme of wynter Aſtronomyers do ete befe / porke / and brawne / hartes / hyndes / and all maner of venyſon / partryches / feſauntes / and fow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>les of the ryuer / and other metes that they lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue beſte. For that is the ſeaſon of the yere that nature ſuffreth moſte great plente of vytay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le / for the naturall hete that is drawen with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the body. In this tyme alſo they drynke of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge wynes after theyr complection / as
<pb facs="tcp:15753:22"/> baſtarde wyne / or oſey. Two or thre tymes in the weke they vſe good ſpyces in theyr me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes. For this is the moſte holſome tyme of all the yere / in the whiche cometh no ſyckeneſſe / but by great exceſſes &amp; outrages done to na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture / or by cuyll gouernynge. Aſtronomyers ſay alſo that Prymetyme is hote and moyſte of the nature of the ayre / complection of the Sanguyne / and that in the ſame tyme natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re reioyſeth / and the poores openeth / and the blode ſpredeth through the vaynes more than in any other tyme. Somer is hote and drye of the nature of the fyre / and of complection coloryke. In the whiche tyme one ought to ke<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pe hym from all thynges that moueth to hete<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>all exceſſe and hote metes. Harueſt is colde &amp; drye of nature of erthe / &amp; complection of mela<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>coly / In the whiche tyme one oughte to kepe hym from doynge exceſſe / more than in other tyme for daunger of ſyckenes / to the whiche that tyme is diſpoſed. But wynter is colde &amp; moyſte of the nature of water / and of comple<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ction flumatyke / than a man oughte for to kepe hym metely warme / and meanely for to lyue in helthe of body.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ Here after foloweth the .iiii. elementꝭ / and the
.iiii. complectione of man. Cap<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> .xiii.</head>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:15753:23"/> 
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Heſe they ben Ayre / Fyre / Erthe / and water. The .xxiiii. houres of the daye &amp; the nyght ruleth San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guyne / Coloryke / Melancoly / &amp; Flumatyke. Sixe houres after mydnyght blode hath the mayſtry / and in the vi. houres before noone Coloure reygneth / and .vi. houres after noone reygneth Melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coly / and the .vi. houres before mydnyght rey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gneth the Flumatyke.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ Here foloweth the Aſtrology of Ptholo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meus. Capitulo
.xiii.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>O as Ptholomeus &amp; alſo dyuers other Aſtronomy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers gyueth vs knowlege of the mouynges and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pryetes of the Heuens: and dyuers other thynges con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayned in this preſent Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſt / the whiche is ſo that eche other may com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pryſe and knowe as they do. Firſt one ought to knowe what the Fygure is / the diſpoſyci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the worlde / the nombre and ordre of the Elementes / and the mouynges of the ſkyes / appertayneth to be knowen of euery man of good and noble wytte. For it is a fayre thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge
<pb facs="tcp:15753:23"/> / delectable / profytable / &amp; honeſt / and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with it is neceſſarye for to haue dyuers other knowleges / and ſpecially the Aſtrology of Ptholomeus: whiche ſheweth how the worl<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de is rounde as a balle. And after wyſe men ſaye that there is no thynge ſo rounde as it is. For it is rounder than any thyng artyfyciall. Yet moreouer in this worlde we ſe no thynge nor neuer ſhall / that is ſo tuſte &amp; egally roun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de as it ſelfe is / and is compoſed of the heuen and the .iiii. Elementes in .v. pryncypall par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyes. After that a man ought to knowe that the erthe is in the myddes of the worlde / for it is the heuyeſt element. And vpon the erthe is the water or the ſee / but it coueryth nat all the erth / to thende that men &amp; beſtꝭ may lyue ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>in / and the partye that is vncoueryd is called the face of the erthe / for it is as the face of man alwayes vncoueryd / and the partye that is coueryd with water is the body of man that is clothed &amp; hydde. On the water is the ayre that encloſeth the erthe and the water / and is deuyded in thre Regyons / one is lowe where<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>as enhabyteth beeſtes and byrdes / another is meane where as ben the cloudes / the whiche make the Impreſſions as lyghtnynges / thon<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dres / and other / and is alwaye colde / and the thyrde is the hyeſt / where as is neyther wyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de
<pb facs="tcp:15753:24"/> nor rayne / nor tempeſt / nor other impreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on / and there ben ſome mountaynes that at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayneth vnto it: as is Olympus that rechyth the hyeſt Regyon of the ayre / and the element of fyre mounteth vnto the ſkye / and the ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes ſuſtayneth the ſkyes / as the pyllers or poſtes ſuſtayneth a houſe. Of ſuche mou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes is one in Affryke named Athlas. After that is the eleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of fyre / that is neyther flam<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>be nor coles / but is pure and inuyſyble: for the great bryghtnes / for of ſo moche as the water is more clere and lyght than the erthe / and the ayre more clere and lyght than the water / of ſo moche the fyre is more clere / lyght / &amp; fayrer than the ayre: and the ſkyes in equipolent ben more clerer / lyghter / and fayrer than the fyre / the whiche tourneth with the mouynges of the heuens / and the next Regyon of the ayre alſo: in the whiche is engendred comytes that ben called ſterres / for that they ben ſhynynge and moueth as the ſterres. After the ſayinge of Ptholomeus and other Aſtrologyens the fyre is inuyſible for his ſubtylyte and nat for his clerenes / for of as moche as a thyng is mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re clere / of ſo moche it is more viſyble / for we ſe the ſkyes wel / but nat the fyre for it is ouer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>moche more ſubtyle than the ayre that is inuy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſyble for the ſame cauſe / the erthe and the wa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter
<pb facs="tcp:15753:24"/> ben thycke / and therfore they ben vyſyble.</p>
               <p>¶ The ſkyes ben neyther properly heuye nor lyght / harde nor ſofte / clere nor derke / hote nor colde / ſwete nor ſoure / coloure nor ſonne / nor ſuche other qualytes / ſaufe that they ben hote in vertue: for they may cauſe hete here byneth by theyr lyghtnes / mouyngꝭ
/ and influences and ben improperly harde / for they maye nat be deuyded nor broken. And alſo they ben im<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>properly coloures of lyght in ſome partyes / &amp; ben thycke / as ben the partyes of the ſterres. In the whiche there maye no ſterre / nor other partye be adiuſted and put to / nor none maye be demynyſſhed nor taken awaye / and they maye neyther encreaſe nor waxe leſſe / nor be of other fygure than rou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de / nor they may nat chaunge / enpayre / nor waxe olde / nor be cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rumped nor altered / but in lyght onely / as in tyme of the eclyps of the Sonne and Moone: nor they maye nat reſte and ſtande ſtyll / nor tourne onely otherwyſe / later nor ſoner / in partye nor in all / nor behaue them otherwyſe than after theyr comyn courſe: but by myracle deuyne: and therfore the ſterres and ſkyes ben of another nature
/ than the elementes and the thyngꝭ in them co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>poſed / the whiche ben tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mutable and corruptyble. The elementꝭ and all thynges of them compoſed / ben encloſed
<pb facs="tcp:15753:25"/> with the firſte ſkye / as the yelke of an egge is encloſed within the whyte / and the firſt ſkye is encloſed of the ſeconde / and the ſeconde in the thyrde / and the thyrde in the fourth / and ſo of other. The firſte ſkye next the elementes is the ſkye of the Moone. And next it is the ſkye of Mercury. And next it the ſkye of Venus. Than is the ſkye of the Sonne. And nexte that the ſkye of Mars. Than is next the ſkye of Iupiter. And than nexte after that is the ſkye of Saturne. And thus ben the ſkyes of the planettꝭ after theyr ordre. The eyght ſkye is of ſterres fyxed / and they ben called ſo / for that they moue more regulerly and after one guyſe than the planettes do. And than aboue that is the firſt mobyle / in the whiche no thyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge apperyth that Aſtrologyens may ſe. The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re ben ſome Aſtrologyens ſay that aboue the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe .ix. ſkyes is one immobyle / for it tourneth nat / and aboue that is one of Cryſtall / ouer the whiche is the ſkye Imperyall / in the whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che is the throne of god / of the whiche ſkye the Aſtronymyers ought nat to ſpeke / but onely of the firſte mobyle / and that it contayneth al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>togyther called the worlde. ¶ Of one thynge they meruayle moche / that is howe god hath diſtrybuted the ſterres / that he hathe put none in the nynthe ſkye / and hathe put ſo many in
<pb facs="tcp:15753:25"/> the eyght ſkye: that they may not be nombred / and in eche of the other .vii. but one onely / as aforeſayd of the ſonne / moone / and ſterres: as euydently apperyth hereafter.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ Here Ptholomeus ſheweth more playnly of the foure Clementes / and of the ſymyly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of the erthe / and howe that euery Pla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>net is one aboue another / &amp; ſheweth whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che of them ben maſculyne / as theſe fyue Saturne / Iupiter / Mars / Sol / &amp; Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cury. And of .ii. femynyne: as Venus / &amp; Luna / and whiche of them is northly / &amp; ſouthly / and whiche ben oryentall / or occydentall. Capitulo .xv.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ome mouyngꝭ ben of the ſkyes and planettes / that excedeth the vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge of the Aſtrologyens as the mouynge of the fyrma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment: in the which ben the ſterres agaynſte the firſte mobyle in an hondred yere one degre / and the mouynge of the planettes in theyr epiſcycles
/ of the whiche howe well that Aſtronomy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers be nat ygnoraunt of all / yet they make no<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mencyon here / for it ſuffyſeth them onely of
<pb facs="tcp:15753:26"/> two / wherof the one is from oryent in to the occydent aboue the erth / and from occydent in to the oryent vnder it / that is called the dyur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall mouynge / that is to ſaye that it maketh from daye to daye .xxiiii. houres / by the whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che mouynge the .ix. ſkye / that is the firſte mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>byle draweth after / &amp; maketh the other ſkyes to tourne that ben vnder it. The other mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is of the .vii. Planettes / and is from oc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cydent to oryent aboue the erthe: and from ory<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ent in to the occydent vnder it / and is contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the firſte / &amp; ben the two mouynges that Aſtrologyens knowlegeth / and howe well that they ben oppoſytees / yet moue they conty<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nually / and ben poſſyble / as it is ſhewed by enſample. If a ſhyp on the ſee came from ory<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ent in to occydent / &amp; that he of his owne mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynge went in the ſhyp ſoftely towarde ory<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent / this man ſhuld moue a double mouynge wherof one ſhulde be of the ſhyp and of hym ſelfe togyder: &amp; the other ſhuld be of his owne mouynge that he maketh ſoftly to warde ory<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>net. Semblably the planettes ben tranſpor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with theyr ſkye from oryent in to occident by the dyurnall mouynge of the firſte mobyle But later and other wyſe than the fyxed ſter<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>res / by that that euery planet hath his propre mouynge contrary to the mouynge of ſterres:
<pb facs="tcp:15753:26"/> For the moone maketh a courſe leſſe in a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth aboute the erth than a ſterre fyxed / &amp; the ſonne a courſe leſſe in a yere: and the other pla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nettes in certayne tyme eche after the qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tyte of his mouynge. Thus it apperyth that the planettes moue two mouynges. Ptholome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us ſaythe / poſe by ymagynacion that all the ſkyes ſeaſed to moue of the dayly mouynge / the moone wolde make a courſe in goynge from the occydent in to the oryent in as moche tyme as laſteth now .xxvii. dayes / and
.viii. houres / and Mercury / Venus / and Sol wol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de make in lyke maner courſe in the ſpace of a yere / and Mars in two yere / and Saturne in .xxx. yere or theraboute. For now they ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke theyr courſe or reuolucions: &amp; accompſyſſhe theyr propre mouynges in the tyme here na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med. The propre mouynge of planettꝭ is nat ſtreyghte from occydent to oryent / but it is a ſyde waye / and Aſtrologyens ſe them ſenſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble / For whan they ſe the moone before a ſter<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re one nyght / the ſeconde / or the thirde nyght / it is behynde nat ſtreyghte towarde oryent / but ſhall be drawen one tyme towarde Sep<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>temtryon / and another tyme towarde myd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day / &amp; this is bycauſe of the latytude or large<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of the zodyake / in the whiche ben the
.xii. ſygnes / vnder whom the planttes reygneth.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:15753:27"/>
               <head>¶ Of the equynocciall and zodyake: that ben in the .ix. ſkyes that contayneth the fyrma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment vnder it. Capitulo .xvi.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S in the concaue of the fir<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſte mobyle Ptholomeus &amp; other Aſtrologyens yma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyneth to be the .ii. cyrcles / and they ben there royall / the one is as ſmall as a ly<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tell threde / &amp; it is called equynocciall / and the other is large in maner of a gyrdle or as a gar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lande of floures / whiche they do call the zo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyake / and theſe two cyrcles deuydeth the one &amp; the other equally but nat ſtreyght / for the zo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dyake croſſeth crokedly / &amp; the places where it croketh / ben ſayd equynoccialles. For to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtande the equynocciall / we ſeſenſybly al the ſkye tourne from oryent in occydent / and it is called the dayly mouynge
/ or dyurnall mouynge / than ought one to ymagyn a ſtrey<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ghte lyne that paſſeth thorughe the mydle of the erth co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>myng from the one ende of the ſkye to the other about the which lyne is made this mouynge / &amp; the two endes ben the two poyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes in the ſkye that moueth nat / and ben cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the poles of the worlde / of the whiche po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les / one is ouer vs by the ſterre of the northe / 
<pb facs="tcp:15753:27"/> that alwayes demonſtreth hym ſelf &amp; aperith to vs / &amp; is the poſe artyke or ſeptemtryonall / and the other is vnder the erthe alwayes hyd called the pole antertyke / or pole auſtrall / in the myddes of the whiche poles / in the firſte mobyle / is the cyrcle equynocciall equally be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in the partye / as in the other of the ſayde poles / and after this cyrcle is made and meſu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red the dayly mouynge of
.xxiiii. houres that is a naturall daye / &amp; it is called equynoccyall For that whan the ſonne is in it / that daye &amp; the nyghte ben equall thorughe the worlde. The large zodyake as ſayd is in the firſt mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byle / and alſo it is a gyrdle manerly fygured and ſette with ymages of ſygnes entrayled ſubtylly and well compoſed / and ſette with fyxed ſterres / as ſhynyng Carbuncles or p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyous Be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mes full of great vertue / ſette by mayſtryſe right nobly aourned: in the whiche zodyake ben .iiii. pryncypall poyntes / that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uydeth them equally in .iiii. partyes. One is hye called the Solſtyce of Somer / whiche whan the ſonne is entred in Cancer / it is the longeſt day of Somer. Another is lowe cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the Solſtyce of wynter: whiche is whan the ſonne is entred in Caprycorne / than it is the ſhorteſt day of wynter / and meane called equynoccyall of Harueſt / that the ſonne en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treth
<pb facs="tcp:15753:28"/> in Libra in the moneth of Septembre. And the other is called the equynoccyall of Prymetyme / that the ſonne entreth in Aries in the moneth of Marche. The which .iiii. par<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyes deuydeth eche in thre egall partyes / &amp; ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>keth .xii. partyes / that ben called ſygnes / as Aries / Taurus / Gemini / Cancer / Leo / Vir<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>go / Libra / Scorpio / Sagittarius / Capricor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus / Aquarius / &amp; Piſces. Aquarius begyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth in the equynoccyall &amp; croſſeth the zodya<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke / and whan the ſonne is there it begynneth to declyne (that is to ſaye) approchynge Sep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temtryon / and to ward vs it extendeth to the oryent. Than is Taurus ſeconde / Gemini the thirde / and ſo of all the other. ¶ Alſo eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſygne is deuyded in .xxx. degrees: and be in the zodyake .CCC .lx. degrees / and euery de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gre deuyded by
.lx. mynutes / euery mynute in lx. ſecondes / euery ſeconde in .lx. thyrdes
/ and this partycion &amp; deuyſyon ſuffyſeth to be vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>derſtande of Aſtronomyers.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ Here after foloweth a very ſubtyll varya<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cion in the ſkye. Capitulo .xvii.</head>
               <p>THe Aſtronomyers do knowlege a ve<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry ſubtyll varyacyon in the ſkye / and is for the ſterres fyxed be nat vnder the ſame
<pb facs="tcp:15753:28"/> degrees of the zodyake that were created by<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cauſe of the mouynge of the fyrmament / the whiche ben agaynſt the firſte mobyle in a .C. yere of one degree / for the whiche mutacyon the ſonne maye haue other regarde to a ſterre / and other ſygnyficacion than it had in the ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me paſſed / and alſo whan that bokes were made / for that the ſterre hath chaunged his de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gree or ſygne vnder which it was. And this often tymes cauſeth them that make Prono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtycacions and Iugeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tꝭ comynge to fayle. ¶ All the cyrcles of the ſkye ben narowe and ſmall / except the zodyake / whiche is large / &amp; contayneth in length .CCC .lx. degrees / and of largeneſſe .xii. the whiche largeneſſe is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyded by the myddes
.vi. degrees on that one ſygne / and .vi. on the other: and this dyuyſion is made by a lyne named Eclyptyke / is the waye of the ſonne / for the ſonne neuer depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth vnder that lyne / and thus it is alway in the mydle of the zodyake / but the other planet<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes ben alwayes on the one ſyde / or on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the ſayd lyne / ſaufe whan they ben in the heed or in the tayle of the Dragon / as the moone paſſeth twyſe in a moneth / and if it happen whan that it reneweth it is Eclypſe of the ſonne / &amp; if it happen in the full moone &amp; that it be ryght vnder the nadyr of the ſon<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e
<pb facs="tcp:15753:29"/> it is generall eclypſe / and if it be but a partye it is nat ſeen. whan it is eclypſe of the ſonne / it is nat generall thorugh all the clymatꝭ but onely in ſome / but whan it is eclypſe of the moone / it is generall ouer all.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ Of .ii. great cyrcles / that is to ſay one mery<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dyen
/ &amp; the other ozyron that interſequeth one the other / and croſſeth dyrectly. Capitulo .xviii.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Eridyen is a great cyrcle yma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gyned on the ſkye / whiche paſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſeth by the poles of the world: and by the poynte of the ſkye right ouer our heedes / whiche is called zenych / and whan the ſon<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e is comen ouer from the orye<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t vnto that cyrcle it is myd<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>day / and therfore it is called merydyen / &amp; the halfe of the cyrcle is ouer the erthe / &amp; the other vnder it that paſſeth by the poynte of myd<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nyght dyrectly oppoſite to zenych / and whan the ſonne toucheth that parte of the cyrcle it is mydnygth
/ and if a man go to warde oryent or occydent he hath newe merydyen / and ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore it is ſoner mydday to them that be to war<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de oryent than to other / if a man ſtande ſtyll / his merydyen is one ſtyll: or if he go to warde
<pb facs="tcp:15753:29"/> mydday or Septemtryon / but if he ſtyre he hath other zenych / and theſe two cyrcles croſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth directly. Ozyron is a great cyrcle that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uydeth the partye of the ſkye that we ſe from that we ſe nat: and Ptholomeus ſayth if that a man were in a playne countre he ſhulde ſe Iuſtly halfe of the ſkye / the whiche is called the Emyſpery (that is to ſay) halfe eſpere and ozyron is ioynynge nyghe to the erthe / of the whiche ozyron the entre is the mydle / and is the place in whiche we ben / thus eche is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes in the myddes of his ozyron / and ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyche is the pole / and as a man tranſporteth hym from one place to another / he is in the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther places agaynſt the ſkye / and hathe other zenyche and other ozyron / all ozyron is ryght or oblyke. They haue right ozyron that haby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth vnder the equynoccyall / and haue theyr zenyche in the equynoccyall / for theyr ozyron interſequeth and deuydeth the equynoccyall euen by the two poles of the worlde / that in ſuche wyſe that none of the poles of the worl<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de is reyſed aboue theyr ozyron / nor depryued vnder it / but they that habyteth other where than vnder the equynoccyall haue theyr ozy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron oblyke / for theyr ozyron foloweth and de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uydeth the equynoccyall ſydewaye / and nat right / and there apperyth to them of al tymes
<pb facs="tcp:15753:30"/> one of the poles of the worlde reyſed aboue theyr ozyron / and the other ben ouer hydde / ſo that they ſe them nat / more or leſſe after dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers habytacions / and after that they ben of fernes from the equynoccyall / and the more that the one pole is reyſed the more is the ozy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron oblyke / and the other pole depryued / and it is to wete that there is as moche dyſtaunce from the ozyron to the pole: as it is from the ze<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nyche to the equynoccyall / and that zenych is the fourth partye of merydyen or the myddes of the bowe dyurnall / of the whiche the two endes ben on the ozyron. And alſo that of the pole vnto the equynoccyall is the fourth par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye of all the roundnes of the ſkyes / and alſo of the merydyen cyrcle ſythe that it paſſeth by the poles &amp; croſſeth the equynoccyall dyrectly. ¶ Example of the ozyron of Parys after the opynyon of Ptholomeus &amp; other Aſtronomy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ers / ouer the whiche ozyron they ſaye that the pole is reyſed
.xlix. degrees: wherfore they ſay alſo that from the zenych of Parys vnto the equynoccyall ben .xlix. degrees / &amp; that from the ozyron vnto the zenych / whiche is the .iiii. partye of the merydyen cycle ben .lxxxx. de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees
/ and from the pole vnto the ſolſtyce of Somer ben .lvii. degrees / &amp; from the ſolſtyce vnto the equynoccyall ben .xxxiii. degrees / 
<pb facs="tcp:15753:30"/> there ben from the pole vnto the equynoccyal lxxxx. degrees / &amp; is the fourthe partye of the roundenes of the ſkye / from the equynoccyall vnto the ſolſtyce of wynter ben .xxxiii. de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees / and from the ſolſtyce vnto the ozyron .xviii. Thus ſhall the equynoccyall ben rey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ouer the ozyron .xli. degrees / and the ſolſty<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce of ſomer
.lxiiii. degrees: in the whiche ſolſty<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce is the ſonne at the houre of noone the lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geſt daye of ſomer: And than it entreth in to the ſy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gne of Cancer / and is moſte nerer our haby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table ꝑtyes that may be. And whan the ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne is in the ſolſtyce of wynter the ſhorteſt day of the yere at the houre of noon it entreth i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the ſygne of Capricorne. And the ſayd ſolſtyce is nat reyſed ouer the ozyron of Parys but .viii. degrees. The whiche cleuacyons &amp; ryſynges a man may fynde playnly / ſo that he knewe one onely / and in euery regyon in lyke wyſe after the ſytuacion.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ Alſo hereafter do folowe two other great cyrcles of the ſkye / &amp; foure ſmall. Ca .xix.</head>
               <p>ON the ſkye ben two great cyrcles na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med coloures / that deuydeth the ſkyes in foure egall partyes / &amp; croſſeth theyr ſelfe dyrectly / and the one paſſeth by the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les
<pb facs="tcp:15753:31"/> of the worlde / and by the two ſolſtyces / and the other by the poles alſo / &amp; by the two equynoccyalles. The firſte ſmall cyrcle is cal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>led the cyrcle artyke bycauſe of the pole zodya<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke aboute the pole artyke / and his lykenes is to his oppoſyte / named the cyrcle antertyke. The other two ben named tropykes / the one of ſomer / and the other of wynter. The tropy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke of ſomer is cauſe of the ſolſtyce of ſomer be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gynnynge of the ſygne of Cancer: and the tro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pyke of the ſolſtyce of wynter begynnyng of the ſygne of Caprycorne / and ben egally dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce one cyrcle from the other. ¶ Here ought to be noted that the dyſtau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces of the pole arty<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke to the cyrcle artyke / and the dyſtau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of the tropyke of ſomer to the equynoccyall / &amp; that of the equynoccyall to the tropyke of wynter: and from the cyrcle antertyke to the pole an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertyke ben iuſte egall eche of .xxiii. degrees &amp; a halfe or there about / than the dyſtau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce from the equynoccyall to the tropyke of ſomer / and from the cyrcle artyke to the pole make togy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther .xlvii. degrees. The whiche take awaye of the quarter bytwene the pole and the equy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>noccyall / where as ben .lxxxx. degrees / ſaue that there abydeth .xliii. That ben the dyſtau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce bytwene the tropyke of wynter and the cyr<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cle antertyke / and theſe cyrcles ben ſayd lytell
<pb facs="tcp:15753:31"/> for they ben nat ſo great as the other ben / Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertheleſſe they ben deuyded eche by .CCC. &amp; .lx. degrees / as the greateſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ Of the ryſynge and reſconſynge of the ſygnes in the ozyron. Capitulo .xx.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>Zyron an emyſpery dyfferred: for ozyron is the cyrcle that de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uydeth the partye of the ſkye / that we ſe / from the vnder the erthe that we ſe nat. Alſo ozyron is the cyrcle that moueth nat / but as we moue from one place to another: but emy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpery tourneth contynually / for one partye ry<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſeth and mounteth ouer ozyron / and the other parte reſconſeth &amp; entreth vnder it / thus ozy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron ryſeth nor reſconſeth: but that that cometh aboue ryſeth and that whiche goth vnder reſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>conſeth / merydyen alſo ryſeth nat nor reſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth. Equynoccyall is the dyurnall cyrcle that ryſeth and reſconſeth reguler: as moche in one houre as in another / and all in .xxiiii: houres: zodyake the large cyrcle and oblyke / wheron the ſygnes ben reyſeth and reſconſeth all on a day naturall / but nat reguler: for it ryſeth mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re in one houre than in another / for that oure ozyron is oblyke and deuydeth the zodyake in
<pb facs="tcp:15753:32"/> two partyes: wherof one is euer ouer our ozy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ron / and the other vnderneth. Thus halfe of the ſygnes ryſeth ouer our ozyron euery daye artyfyciall / be it ſhorte or longe / and the other halfe by nyghte / wherfore it behoueth that in the dayes that ben ſhorter than the nyghte the ſygnes ryſeth ſoner / and in longe dayes more at leyſer / and thus the zodyake ryſeth nat re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulerly in theſe partyes as the equynocciall / But there is dowble varyacion for halfe of the zodyake that is from the firſte begyn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ynge of Aries vnto the laſte ende of Virgo / all to<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gyther taketh equally as moche tyme in riſyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge / as halfe of the equynocciall the whiche re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayneth by it / and they do begyn to ryſe in a moment: and alſo they fynyſſhe &amp; make theyr ende in a moment. But this halfe of the zody<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ake ryſeth ſoner in the begynnynge / and this halfe of the equynoccyall more at leyſer / and this is called theyr oblyquement. ¶ Alſo the other halfe of the zodyake / that is from the be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gynnynge of Libra vnto the ende of Piſces / and halfe of the equynocciall that by it begyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neth / and alſo it leueth to ryſe equally togy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther / but the equynocciall in that partye in the begynnynge ryſeth ſoner / &amp; the zodyake more at leyſer / and this is called ryſynge dyrectly. And whiche that ryſeth ſoner the equynoccy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all
<pb facs="tcp:15753:32"/> or the zodyake / yet alwayes they ende to gyther. Example of the two mouyngꝭ afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayd / as if two men wente from London to wyndſore and departed both togyther / &amp; that at the begynnynge the one go faſt / &amp; the other ſoftely / he that gothe faſt ſhuld be ſoner in the mydwaye than the other / but if he that went faſt to the mydway go ſoftely / and the other faſte / they ſhall be both at ones in wyndſore. Alſo the halfe of the zodyake: from the begyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nynge of Cancer / vnto the ende of Sagitta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in ryſynge beryth more than halfe the equy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>noccyall / ſo that this halfe ryſeth all ryght / &amp; the other halfe of the zodyake ryſeth contrary<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wyſe / or croked.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ Of the deuyſyons of the erthe / and of the regyons. Capitulo .xxi.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Efore or we ſpere of the ſter<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>res &amp; knowlege that Ptho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomeus and other Aſtrono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myers haue / we wyll ſpeke of the deuyſyon of the erthe / &amp; of his partyes after theyr opynyon. wherfore it is to be noted that the erthe is rounde / and therfore as a man go the from one countre to another / he hath other ozy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ron
<pb facs="tcp:15753:33"/> than he had / and there apperyth another partye of the ſkye / &amp; if a man went from ſep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temtryon that is the North partyes ſtreyghte towarde mydday / the South partyes the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le artyke to hym ſhal be leſſe reyſed / that is to ſay more nyghe approchynge to the erthe: and if he went contrary wyſe it ſhuld be more rey<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed / that is to ſay apperynge hygher / and ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore if he went towarde mydday vnder me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rydyen whyle that the pole artyke were leſſe reyſed ouer his ozyon by the .xxx. parte of one of the .vi. parte of the arke merydyen: he ſhuld paſſe the
.xxx. partes of halfe of the cyrcuyte of the erthe / and to hym the pole ſhuld be leſſe reyſed by one degree / or to the contrary tyll it were more reyſed of one degree / than he ſhuld paſſe one degree of the cyrcuyte of the erthe / of the which al the degrees togyther ben .CCC .lx. And one degree of the erth co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tayneth .xliii .leges &amp; a halfe or there aboute / and euery lege<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>is .ii. myle. And as the ſpere of the ſkye is deuy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded by the .iiii .leſſe cyrcles in the .v. partes cal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>led zones / ſo the erthe is deuyded in to .v. regy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ons. ¶ The firſte is bytwene the pole artyke and the cyrcle artyke. The .ii .is bytwene the cyrcle artyke and the tropyke of ſomer. The .iii .is bytwene the tropyke of ſomer / and the tropyke of wynter. The .iiii .is bytwene the
<pb facs="tcp:15753:33"/> tropyke of wynter / and the cyrcle antertyke. The
.v. bytwene the cyrcle antertyke and the pole antertyke. Of the whiche partyes of the erthe / ſome Aſtronymyers ſaye that the firſte &amp; the .v. ben inhabytable / for theyr ouer great coldenes / for they ben to ferre from the ſonne. The thirde that is in the mydle is to nere vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der the way of the ſonne / and is nat inhaby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table for the great hete. The other .ii. partyes / the ſeconde and the fourthe be nat to nere nor to ferre from the ſonne / but ben moderate in hete and colde / and therfore they ben habyta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble if there be none other lettynge / and ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe that it be true / yet it is nat poſſyble to paſſe ouerth warte the Regyon vnder the waye of the ſonne called zone / tourned, to go from the ſeconde to the fourth / for ſome Aſtronomyers wolde haue paſſed / that wolde haue ſhewed of it / wherfore they ſay that there is no Regy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on habyted / but the ſeconde wherin we and all the other ben alſo.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ Of the varyacion that is for dyuers haby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacions &amp; regyons of the erth. Cap<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> .xxii.</head>
               <p>PTholomeus and other Aſtronomyers ſaye / that if it were poſſyble that the erthe were enhabyted all aboute and poſe the
<pb facs="tcp:15753:34"/> caſe that it were ſo / firſte they that enhabyte vnder the equynoccyall / haue alwayes the dayes and the nyghtes egall
/ &amp; haue the two poles of the world at the two corners of their ozyron / and may ſe all the ſterres whan they ſe the two poles / and the ſon<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e paſſeth twyſe in a yere ouer them / that is whan it paſſeth by the equynoccyalles. Thus the ſonne is to them the one halfe of the yere towarde the po<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>le artyke / &amp; the other halfe towarde the other pole / and therfore they haue two wynters in a yere without great colde / one is whan we haue wynter / &amp; the other whan we haue ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer. Semblably they haue two ſomers / one is in Marche whan we haue prymetyme / &amp; the other in Septembre whan we haue Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſt / and by this they haue foure Solſtyces / two hye whan the ſonne paſſeth by theyr ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyche / and two lowe whan it declyneth one waye or other / and thus they haue foure ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes in a yere / for whan the ſonne is in the equynocces twyſe in one yere in the mornyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge theyr ſhadowes ben in the occydent: and at nyghte in the oryent / and than at noone they haue no ſhadowes / but whan the ſon<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e is in the ſygnes Septemtryonalles / &amp; ſo agayne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde. Secondely they that enhabyte by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twene the equynoccyal and the tropyke of ſo
<pb facs="tcp:15753:34"/> mer / haue in lykewyſe two ſomers and two wynters / and foure ſhadowes in a yere / and they haue no dyfference of the firſte / ſaue that they haue longer dayes in ſomer / and ſhorter in wynter / for as the equynoccyall lengeth / in lykewyſe doth the dayes of ſomer / and in the partye of the erth is the firſte clymate and almoſte halfe the ſeconde / &amp; is called Araby wherin is Ethyope. Thirdely they that enha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>byte vnder the tropyke of ſomer haue the ſon<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne ouer theyr hedes
/ &amp; the daye of Solſtyce of ſomer at noone / they haue theyr ſhadowes ſmaller than we haue / and there is a partye of Ethyope. Fourthly they that ben bytwene the tropyke of ſomer &amp; the cyrcle artyke / haue longer dayes in ſomer than the aforeſayd / in as moch as they ben ferther from the equynoc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyall / &amp; ſhorter in wynter / and they neuer ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue the ſonne ouer theyr hedes / nor toward ſep<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>temtryon / and that partye of the erth we en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habyte. Fyfthly they that enhabyte vnder the cyrcle artyke haue the eclyptyke of the zodya<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke to theyr ozyron / and whan the ſonne is in the Solſtyce of ſomer it reſconſeth nat: &amp; thus they haue no nyghte / but naturall dayes of .xxiiii. houres. Semblably whan the ſon<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e is in the Solſtyce of wynter it is naturall daye whan they haue contynuall nyght / and that
<pb facs="tcp:15753:35"/> the ſon<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e ryſeth nat to them. Syxtly they that ben bytwene the cyrcle artyke and the pole ar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyke haue in ſomer dyuers natural dayes that ben to them one daye artyfyciall without ny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghte. And alſo in wynter ben many natural dayes: the whiche naturall dayes ben to them alwayes nyght / &amp; the more that it approcheth or draweth nere the pole / the more is the arty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyciall daye of ſomer longe / &amp; dureth in ſome place a weke: in ſome a moneth / in ſome two in ſome thre / &amp; in ſome more
/ &amp; proporcyonal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the nyght is greater / for ſome of the ſygnes ben euer on theyr ozyron / and ſome alwayes vnder / &amp; as longe as the ſon<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e is in the ſygnes aboute it is daye / and whyle it is vnderneth it is nyght. Seuenthly they that enhabyte vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der the pole haue the ſon<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e halfe of the yere on theyr ozyron / and haue contynuall daye / and the other halfe of the yere contynuall nyght / and the equynoccyall is theyr ozyron that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uydeth the ſygnes .vi. aboue / and .vi. byneth wherfore whan the ſon<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e is in the ſygnes that ben hye / and towarde them they haue conty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall daye. And whan it is in the ſygnes to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde mydday they haue contynuall nyght: and thus in a yere they haue but one day and one nyghte. And as it is ſayd of the partye of the erthe towarde the pole artyke a man may
<pb facs="tcp:15753:35"/> vnderſtande of the other halfe and of the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bytactons towarde the pole antertyke.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ Of the deuyſyon of the erthe / and onely of the parte enhabyted. Capitulo .xxiii.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>O as Ptholomeus &amp; dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers other deuyden the erth habytable in .vii. partyes / that they call Clymates &amp; the dyamerous. The .ii. cly<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mate dyatyens. The .iii. da<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lyxandrye. The .iiii. dyar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hodes. The .v. dyaromes. The .vi. daboriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. And the .vii. dyaripheos / of the whiche eche hathe his longytude determyned / and the latytude alſo / and nerer they ben to the equy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocciall the longer they ben / and larger / and procede in longytude from oryent to occydent and in latytude from mydday to ſeptemtry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. The firſt clymate after ſome Aſtronomy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ers conteyneth in length halfe of the cyrcuyte of the erthe / that is two hondreth thouſande / and foure hondreth myle / and it hath an hon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreth thouſande / and two hondreth myles of length. The. ſeconde / and ſo of the other / for the leſſynge of the erth comynge towarde ſep<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>temtryon. To vnderſtande what a clymate
<pb facs="tcp:15753:36"/> is after the ſayinge of Aſtronomyers. A cly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate is a ſpace of the erth egally large / wher of the length is from oryent to occydent / and the bredthe is comynge from mydday &amp; from the erthe enhabytable towarde the equynoccy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>all drawynge to ſeptemtryon / as moche as an horologe or clocke chaungeth nat. For in erthe habytable the clockes chaungeth .vii. ty<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mes in the bredthe of the clymates / it is of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſyte to ſay that they ben .vii. and where the varyacion of horologes is / there is the dyuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyte of clymates / howe be it that ſuche varya<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyon properly oughte to be taken in the myd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of the clymatꝭ / and nat at the begynnyng nor in the ende / for the nereneſſe &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uenaunce the one of the other. Alſo one clymate hath al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wayes a day artyfycyall of ſomer / ſhorter or longer than another clymate / and this daye ſheweth the dyfference in the myddes of eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry clymate / better than in the myddes &amp; at the ende / the whiche thynge we maye ſenſybly knowe at iye: and therby Iudge the dyfferen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce of the clymatꝭ. ¶ And it is to be noted that vnder the equynoccyall the dayes &amp; the nygh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes in all tymes are egall eche of .xii. houres / but comynge towarde ſeptemtrion the dayes of ſomer longeth / and the wynter dayes ſhor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teth / and the more that one approcheth ſeptem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tryon
<pb facs="tcp:15753:36"/> / the more waxeth the dayes in ſuch wy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe that at the ende of the laſte clymate the day<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>es in ſomer ben longer by thre houres and an halfe / than they ben at the begynnynge of the firſte: and the pole is more reyſed by .xxxviii. degrees. At the begynnynge of the firſte cly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate the lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geſt daye of ſomer hath .xii. houres and .xlv. mynutes / and the pole is reyſed on the ozyron .xii. degrees and .xlv. mynutes / &amp; in the myddes of the clymate the longeſt daye hath .xiii. houres / and the pole reyſed .xvi. de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees / and the latytude dureth vnto the lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt daye of ſomer / that is .xiii. houres &amp; .xv. mynutes: and the pole reyſed
.xx. degrees and an halfe / the whiche largenes is .CCCC.xl. myle of erth. The ſeconde clymate begynneth at the ende of the firſte / and the myddes is the<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re as the daye hath .xiii. houres &amp; an halfe / and the pole is reyſed ouer the ozyron .xxiiii. degre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>es / &amp; .xv. mynutes. And the latytude dureth vnto there as the longeſt daye hath .xiii. hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res / and .xlv. mynutes / and the pole is reyſed xxvii. degrees / &amp; an halfe / and this largenes conteyneth of erthe .CCCC. myles Iuſte. The .iii. clymate begynneth at the ende of the ſeconde &amp; the myddes is there as the daye hath xiii. houres / &amp; the pole is reyſed .xxx. degrees / &amp; .xlv. mynutes / and the latytude extendeth
<pb facs="tcp:15753:37"/> vnto there as the longeſt daye hath .xiiii. hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res / &amp; .xv. mynutes / &amp; the pole is reyſed .xxiii. degrees / and
.xl. mynutis. The .iiii. clymate begynnynge at the ende of the thirde / and the myddes is there as the longeſt day hath .xiiii. houres and an halfe / and the pole is reyſed .xxvi. degrees / and .xx. mynutes / the latytu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de dureth vnto there as the longeſt day hath .xiii. houres / and .xlv. mynutes / and the pole is reyſed .xxx. degrees / and the largenes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyneth of erthe .CCC. myle. The .v. clyma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te begynneth at the ende of the fourth: and the myddes is there as the longeſt daye hath .xv. houres / &amp; the pole is reyſed .xli. degrees / &amp; .xx. mynutes / and the latytude dureth vnto there as the longeſt day hath .xv. houres / and .xv. mynutes / and the pole is reyſed
.xliii. degrees and an halfe / and the largenes conteyneth of erthe .CC.lii. myles. The .vi. clymate begyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth at the ende of the fyfthe / and the myddes is there as the longeſt daye hath .xv. houres &amp; an half / and the pole is reyſed ouer the ozyron xlv. degrees / &amp; .xxiii. mynutes / of the whiche the largenes dureth vnto there as the longeſt daye hath .xv. houres / and
.xlv. mynutes: the whiche largenes conteyneth of erthe .CC.xii. myles. The
.vii. clymate begyn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>eth at the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de of the ſyxte / and the myddes is there as the
<pb facs="tcp:15753:37"/> longeſt daye hath .xvi. houres: and the pole is reyſed .xlviii. degrees and .xl. mynutes / the la<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tytude extendeth vnto / there as the longeſt daye hath xvi. houres / and .xv. mynutꝭ / and the pole is reyſed .l. degrees and an halfe / and the largenes of the erthe conteyneth .C.lxxx. and .vi. myles.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ The great and meruaylous conſyderacy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons &amp; great vnderſtandynge of the Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomyers / &amp; Aſtrologyens. Cap<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
.xxiiii.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Fter the lengthe of the cly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mates / ſo if caſe were one myghte go aboute the erth from oryent to occydent to his firſte place: ſome Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nomyers ſay that this com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>paſſe may almoſte be made. Sayinge that if a man wente this compaſſe in .xii. naturall dayes goynge regulerly to warde occydent / &amp; began nowe at mydday / he ſhuld paſſe euery<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>daye naturall the .xii. parte of the cyrcuyte of the erthe / and ben
.xxx. degrees / wherof beho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ueth that the ſonne make a courſe aboute the erth &amp; .xxx. degrees ferther / or he be retourned on the morowe at the merydyen of the ſayde man / and ſo the ſayd man ſhuld haue his day
<pb facs="tcp:15753:38"/> and nyght of .xxvi. houres / and ſhuld be fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by the .xii. parte of a naturall day than if he reſted hym / wherfore it foloweth of neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyte that in .xii. naturall dayes / the ſayd man ſhuld onely haue but a .xi. dayes / and a .xi. ny<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ghtes / and ſomwhat leſſe / and that the ſon<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e ſhuld lyght hym but a .xi. tymes: and reſconſe a .xi. tymes / for a .xi. dayes / and a .xi. nyghtes euery daye &amp; nyghte of .xxvi. houres maketh .xii. naturall dayes / euery daye of
.xxiiii. hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res. By ſemblable co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſideracion behoueth that another man that ſhuld make this courſe go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge towarde oryent haue his daye &amp; nyghte ſhorter than a naturall daye by two houres / than his daye and nyght ſhulde be but of .xii. houres. Than if he made this courſe in lyke ſpace / that is to ſaye in .xii. dayes &amp; ſomwhat more. Thus if Iohan made courſe towarde occydent / and Peter towarde oryent / &amp; that Robert abode them in the place from whenſe they departed the one as ſoone as the other / &amp; that they mette at Robert bothe togyther. Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter wolde ſaye that he hadde
.ii. dayes / and .ii. nyghtes more than Iohan / and Robert that hath reſted a daye leſſe than Peter / and a day more than Iohan / howe well that they haue made this courſe in .xii. naturall dayes or an .C. or in .x. yere / all is one. This is a pleaſau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t
<pb facs="tcp:15753:38"/> conſyderacion amonge Aſtronomyers howe Iohan &amp; Peter cometh in one ſelfe daye / put caſe it were on a ſondaye. Iohan wolde ſay it is ſaterday. Peter wolde ſay it is monday / and Robert wolde ſay it is ſonday.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ Of the Pomell of the ſkyes a ſterre called the ſterre of the northe / nere the whiche is the pole artyke called ſeptemtryonall. Capitulo .xxv.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Ere wyll we ſpeke after the aboueſayd thynges / of ſome ſterres in pertyculer. And firſte of them that Ptholomeꝰ &amp; other Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nomyers nameth the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mell of the ſkyes / or ſterre of the northe / wherfore we ought to knowe that we ſe by reaſon the ſkye tourne from ory<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ent to occydent / by the dyurnall or the dayly mouynge / that is of the firſt mobyle / the whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che is made on two poyntꝭ oppoſytꝭ that ben the poles of the ſkye / of the whiche two poyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes / we do ſe one vyſybly / and it is the pole<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>artyke / and the other we ſe nat / that is the po<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>le antertyke or in mydday / whiche is alway hydde vnder the erth. By the pole artyke that we ſe is the ſterre moſte approched that Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nomyers

<pb facs="tcp:15753:39"/> call the pomell of the ſkye / the whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che they ſaye is the hygheſt &amp; moſte ferre from vs / and by the whiche they haue the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege that they haue of the other ſterres &amp; party<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>es of the ſkye. The ſterres that ben by the ſay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de pomell go neuer vnder the erth / of the whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che ben the ſterres that maketh the charyot / &amp; dyuers other / but they that ben ferre from it / gothe ſomtyme vnder the erthe as the ſonne / the moone and other planettes. Vnder this po<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mell dyrectly is the angle of the erthe / in the place where agaynſt the ſonne is at the houre of mydde nyghte.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="26" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ Of Andromeda a ſterre fyxed. Capitulo .xxvi.</head>
               <p>Aries is a ſygne hote and drye / that go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerneth the hede and the face of man / &amp; the regyons / Babylone / Percy / &amp; Ara<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>by. And ſygnyfyeth ſmall trees / and vnder hym at the .xvi. degree / ryſeth a ſterre fyxed called Andromeda: that Aſtronomyers fygu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>reth a mayden in her heer vpon the brynke of the ſee / ſette to be deuoured of the monſtres of the ſee / but Perſeus ſone of Iupiter foughte with his ſwerde agaynſt the ſayd monſtre &amp; flewe it / &amp; than the ſayde Andromeda was delyueryd. They that ben borne vnder her co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtellacion ben in daunger of pryſon / or to dye
<pb facs="tcp:15753:39"/> in pryſon / but if a good Planet take regarde they ſcape nat dethe and pryſon. Aries is the exaltacion of the ſonne at the .xix. degree: and Aries is the howſe of Mars with Scorpio / wherin he is moſte.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="27" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ Of Perſeus a ſterre fyxed / lorde of the ſpere. Cap<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> .xxvii.</head>
               <p>TAurus hath the trees / plantꝭ / &amp; ympes and gonerneth the necke and the throte bolle of man / the regyons Ethyopy / Egypte / and the countre aboute / and vnder the .xxii. degree ryſeth a ſterre fyxed of the fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſte magnytude that Aſtronomyers call Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeus ſone of Iupiter that ſmote of the heed of Meduſe that made all them to dye that behel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de her / and by no maner they myght eſchewe it. Ptholomeus and other Aſtronomyers ſay that whan Mars is conioyned with this ſter<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re. They that ben borne vnder the conſtella<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyon ſhall haue theyr heedes ſmyten of / if god ſhape nat remedy: and ſomtyme they call this ſterre lorde of the ſwerde
/ and fygure hym a man naked with a ſwerde in one hande / and in the other the heed of Meduſe &amp; loketh nat on it. And this ſygne Taurus is the exaltaci<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on of the moone in the thyrde degree.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="28" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ Of Ozyron a ſterre fyxed / and the felawes. Capitulo
.xxviii.</head>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:15753:40"/> GEmini ſygnyfyeth large / good coura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge / wytte / beaute / clergy / &amp; gouerneth of man the ſholdres / armes / and han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des / and the regyons Ynde / Armony / Carta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge / and hath the ſmall trees. And vnder the .xviii. degree ryſeth a ſterre fyxed called Ozy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ron / and with it
.xxxvi. other ſterres / and is fygured a man armed in mayle / and a ſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de gyrde aboute hym / and ſygnyfyeth great captaynes. They that ben borne vnder the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtellacion ben in daunger to be ſlayne by trea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſon / if good fortune be nat with them. Gemi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ni and Virgo ben the houſes of Mercury / but Virgo is it / in the whiche he ioyeth moſt / and Gemini in the .iii. degree is the exaltacyon of the dragons hede.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="29" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ Of Alhabor a ſterre fyxed. Capitulo .xxix.</head>
               <p>CAncer gouerneth the longe &amp; the egall trees / and of the body of man the breſte the herte / the ſtomacke / the ſyde / the ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghtes
/ and the lunges / the regyons Armonye the lytell / and the regyon of oryent. And there ryſeth vnder it in the .viii. degree a ſterre fyx<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed that Aſtronomyers calle Alhabor (that is to ſaye) of the great dogge / and they ſaye that they whiche ben borne vnder the conſtellacy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: and that ben in the aſcendynge or the myd<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des
<pb facs="tcp:15753:40"/> of the ſkye it ſygnyfyeth good fortune / &amp; if the moone be with it / and the partye of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune / he that in it ſhall be borne / ſhall nat be very ryche / and Cancer the ſygne ſo called / is the houſe of the moone / and is the exaltacy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on of Iupiter in the .xv. degree.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="30" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ Of the Lyons herte a ſterre fyxed. Capitulo
.xxx.</head>
               <p>LEo hath the great trees (that is to ſaye) he is lorde ouer them and ſygnyfieth an haſty man full of angre &amp; of anguſſhe / and of the body of man / it behoueth properly the herte / the backe and the ſydes. And of regy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ons Tartary / vnto the ende of the erthe haby<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>table / and vnder the .xxxiii. degtee ryſeth a ſterre fyxed called the Lyons herte / and they that ben borne vnder that conſtellacyon / as Aſtronomyers ſaye / ſhall be mounted in hye ſygnouryes / or in great offyces / &amp; afterwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de ſhall be depryued or put downe / and be in daunger of theyr lyues
/ but if ſome good pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net beholde the ſayd ſterre they may nat be ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ued. Leo is the houſe of the ſonne / and Aries is the exaltacyon of the ſonne / as it is ſayd of Ptholomeus and of other.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="31" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ Of the ſterre fyxed called Nebuluſe / &amp; of another called the golden Cuppe.</head>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:15753:41"/> VIrgo gouerneth all that is ſowen on erthe / and ſygnyfyeth a man of good courage / Phyloſophre plentuous / &amp; of all maner of ſcyences / and kepeth of man the bely &amp; the entrayles / And the regyon Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geramyta / Aſſen / that is a regyon by Ihe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem / Eufrates / and the yle of Spayne. Vnder the longytude or .xv. degree ryſeth a ſterre fyxed named Nebuluſe or tayle of the Lyon / and in Septemtryonall latytude of the ſayd ſygne of virgo. Vnder the whiche ſy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gne ryſeth another fyxed ſterre / which Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nomyers calle the golden cuppe / and is in the .xiii. degree of the ſayd ſygne towarde the par<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tye merydyonall. The whiche ſterre is of the nature of Venus and of Mercury: and ſygny<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fyeth that they
/ whiche ben borne vnder the ſayd conſtellacion to knowe of thyngꝭ wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy / good / and holy.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="32" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ Of the Porke eſpyke a ſterre fyxed. Capitulo
.xxxii.</head>
               <p>LIbra that vnder this ſygne domyneth the great trees / and ſygnyfyeth Iuſtyce and of man it gouerneth the reynes / &amp; the nether parte of the bely / And regyons the countre of Romany and of Grece. Vnder the xviii. degree ryſeth a ſterre fyxed that Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomyers calle Porke eſpyke. They that ben
<pb facs="tcp:15753:41"/> borne vnder the conſtellacyon ben well ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen
/ and ben honeſt / and do thyngꝭ that folke meruayle on / and reioyſeth / and ſygnyfyeth ryches by honeſt and precyous marchaundyſe and ben comonly loued of lordes and ladyes and Libra is one of the houſes of Venus / and Taurus is the other / in the whiche ſhe reioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth moſt. And is the exaltacion of Saturne For the wether begynneth to waxe colde in this monthe of Septembre / and Saturne is the planet and the lorde of colde that exalteth in great heyghte / whan that he entreth in to the ſygne of Libra.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="33" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ Of the Crowne ſeptemtryonall a ſterre fyxed. Capitulo .xxxiii.</head>
               <p>SCorpio that domyneth the trees that ben of longytude and largenes / and ſygnyfyeth falſenes / and of the body of man gouerneth the preuy places / and the re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gyons of Heberget: and the felde of Araby in the .ii. degree ryſeth a ſterre / that Aſtronomy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers call the Crowne ſeptemtryonal / the whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che whan it is in the aſcendynge in the myd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of the ſkye gyueth honoure and exaltacy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to them that ben borne vnder the conſtella<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyon / &amp; ſpecyally whan it is well beholden of Sol / the Scorpion is one of the houſes of Mars / in the whiche he reioyſeth moſte
/ and
<pb facs="tcp:15753:42"/> Aries is the other / and is the Sygne wherin Mars begynneth to deſcende or fall from his exaltacyon.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="34" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ Of the Scorpyons herte a ſterre fyxed. Capitulo
.xxxiiii.</head>
               <p>SAgittary ſygnyfieth the man ingeny<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ous &amp; wyſe / and gouerneth the thy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghes of man / And regyons Ethyope Maharobem / and Aenyche. Vnder his firſte degree ryſeth a ſterre fxyed of the firſt magny<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tude / the which Aſtronomyers call the Scor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pyons herte / whiche whan it is well behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den of Iupiter or Venus / it reyſeth them that ben borne vnder his conſtellacion to great ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>noure and rycheſſe / but whan it is euyl behol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>den of Saturne or of Mars / it putteth them that ben borne vnder it to pouerte / the Scor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyon is the houſe of Iupiter / in the whiche he reioyſeth moſte / and Piſces is the other houſe: and ſo is he ſayde Sagittary / the exaltacion of the dragons tayſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="35" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ Of the flyinge Egle a ſterre fyxed. Capitulo
.xxxv.</head>
               <p>CApricornus ſygnyfieth a man of good and perfyte lyfe / wyſe
/ yrefull / and of great thought: and gouerneth the knees of man / and the regyons Ethyopye / Araby / Behamen / and to the two ſees / and vnder
<pb facs="tcp:15753:42"/> his .xxviii. degree ryſeth a ſterre / that Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomyers call the flyinge Egle / that ſygnyfy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eth the ſouerayne or myghty Emperoures / or kynges. They that ben borne vnder his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtellacion / whan they ben well begolden of the ſonne of Iupiter mounteth in great ſyg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouryes / and ben loued of kynges and pryn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces / Capricornus and Aquarius ben the hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of Saturne / but he reioyſeth in Aquary moſte: and the ſygne of the ſayd Capricornus is the exaltacion of Mars.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="36" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ Of the Fyſſhe merydyonall a ſterre fyxed. Capitulo .xxxvi.</head>
               <p>AQuarius that kepeth the ſhankes vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ancles of the fete of man / and the regyons / Hazenoth / Aſempha / &amp; par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye of the lande of Alphege / &amp; parte of Egy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pte / the .xxi. degree ryſeth a ſterre / that Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomyers call the Fyſſhe merydyonall. They that ben borne vnder this conſtellacyon ben happy in fyſſhynge in the ſouthe ſee / and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the .ix. degree of the ſayde ſygne ryſeth the Dolphyn that ſygnyfieth lordſhyp on the ſee on pondes / &amp; ryuers / and as it is ſayd / Aqua<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rius is the houſe of Saturne / in the whiche he reioyſeth hym.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="37" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ Of Pegaſus that ſygnyfyeth the Horſe of honour a ſterre fyxed. Cap<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> .xxxvii.</head>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:15753:43"/> PIſces gouerneth of man the fete / and ſygnyfyeth a man ſubtyll / wyſe / and of dyuers coloures / and hath regyons Trapeſen / Iurgen / and al the habytable par<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tye / that is ſeptemtryon / and parte of Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny / &amp; vnder the .xv. degree of the ſayde ſygne ryſeth a ſterre that Aſtronomyers call Pega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus / that is the Horſe of honoure / &amp; the fygure in forme of a fayre horſe. They that ben bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne vnder this conſtellacyon ſhalbe honoured amonge great captaynes and lordes / whan Venus is with it / they be loued of great La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyes if the ſayde ſterre be in the myddes of the ſkye in the deſcendynge / and Piſces is one of the houſes of Iupiter / and Sagittarius the other / in the whiche he reioyſeth moſte / &amp; the ſayd Piſces in the .xxvii. degree is the exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacyon of Venus.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="38" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ Of the deuyſyon of the twelue houſes / as well in the erthe as in the heuens / as hereafter do folowe. Cap<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> .xxxviii.</head>
               <p>IT is to vnderſtande that the Heuens &amp; the erthe is deuyded in .iiii. partyes by .ii. cyrcles: whiche croſſetſ, dyrectly ouer the two poles / and croſſeth .iiii. tymes the equy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noccyal lyne. Eche of the .iiii. partyes deuyded
<pb facs="tcp:15753:43"/> in .iii. egally / is in all twelue egall partes / as well in the ſkye as in the erthe / whiche Ptho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lomeus and other calle howſes / and ben .xii. Of whiche .vi. ben alwayes aboue the erthe And .vi
.vnder it: and theſe houſes moue nat but ben alwayes eche in his place / and the ſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnes and Planettes paſſe by them alwayes ones in .xxiiii. houres. Thre of theſe howſes ben from oryent to mydnyght goynge vnder the erthe / The firſte / the ſeconde / and the thyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de / wherof the firſte vnder the erthe begyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth in oryent / named the houſe of lyfe. The ſeconde houſe is named of ſubſtaunce and ry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches. The thirde that finyſſheth at mydnyght is the houſe of fraternyte. The fourth that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gynneth at mydnyght comynge in occydent / is named the houſe of patrymony. The fyfte is the houſe of ſonnes. The ſyxte fynyſſheth in occydent / vnder the erthe is the houſe of ſyc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kenes. The ſeuenth begynneth in occydent on the erthe / and ſtretcheth towarde mydday / is the houſe of maryage. The eyght is the houſe of dethe. The nynthe fynyſſhyng at mydday is named the houſe of feyth / of relygyon / and pylgrymag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. The tenthe begynneth at myd<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>day comynge towarde oryent / is the houſe of honour and of regalyte. The enleuenth is the very houſe of true frendes. And the twelthe
<pb facs="tcp:15753:44"/> that fynyſſheth in oryent on the erthe / is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the houſe of charyte / but this mater is dyf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fycyle / for Aſtronomyers knowlegynge the nature and propryte of euery of the ſayde
.xii. houſes / and departeth them lyghtly.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="39" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ Howe the Planettes reygne in eury houre of the day and the nyght. Cap<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> .xxxix.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>E that wyll wete howe Aſtronomyers knoweth whiche Planet reygneth euery hour of the day and the nyght / and which pla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>net is good / and which is badde / he oughte firſte to knowe the planet of the day: and for to ſerche therfore. The firſt temporall houre of the ſon<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne ryſynge / that daye is for the ſayde planet. The ſeconde houre is for the planet enſuyng And the thirde for the other / &amp; ſo folowynge by ordre / and it behoueth to goo from Sol to Venus / Mercury &amp; Luna / than come agayne to Saturne vnto .xii. that is the houre before the ſonne goynge downe / and in contynent after the ſonne is downe / begynneth the firſte houre of the nyght: that is for the .viii. planet: and the ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de houre of the nyght for the .xiiii.
<pb facs="tcp:15753:44"/> and ſo vnto .xii. houres for the nyght / that is the nexte houre before the ſonne ryſynge / and come dyrectly fallynge vpon the .xxiiii. pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net / that is next before that the day folowyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge. And thus the day hath .xii. houres / and the nyght .xii. alſo / the whiche ben temporall hou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>res / dyfferent to the houres of the clockes / the whiche ben artyfycyalles. Ptholomeus and other Aſtronomers ſay that Saturne &amp; Mars ben euyll planettes / Iupiter &amp; Venus good / Sol and Luna halfe good / and halfe euyll. The partie to warde the good planet is good and the partye to warde the euyll planette is nought. Mercury conioyned with a good pla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>net is good / and with an euyll planette he is nought / and they vnderſtande this as the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluencꝭ good or euyll / that ben of the ſayd pla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nettes here folowynge. ¶ The houres of the planettes ben dyfferent to them of clockes: for the houres of clockes ben egall at all tymes / eche of .lx. mynutes / but they of the planettes whan the dayes &amp; the nyghtes ben egall that the ſonne is in one of the equynocces they ben egall / But as ſoone as the dayes longeth or ſhorteth / ſo dothe the naturall houres / by this it is conuenyent alwaye for the daye to haue .xii. temporall houres / and the nyght
.xii. alſo: and whan the dayes ben longe / &amp; the houres
<pb facs="tcp:15753:45"/> longe: and whan the dayes ben ſhorte and the houres ſhorte / in lykewyſe is the nyght / and neuertheleſſe an houre of the day / and an hou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re of the nyght togyther haue .vi. ſcore mynu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes / as many as two houres artyfycyalles / for that the one leueth / the other taketh. And take we our planettes / from the ſonne ryſyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge vnto the ſon<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e goynge downe: &amp; nat before and all the remenaunt is nyght.</p>
               <div type="example">
                  <head>¶ An example of this aforeſayd.</head>
                  <p>IN decembre the dayes haue but viii. hou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>res artyfycialles of clockes / and they ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue .xii. temporalles / lette the .viii. houres artyfycialles ben deuyded in .xii. egall party<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es / and it ſhalbe .xii. tymes
.xl. mynutes / and euery partye ſhalbe a temporall houre / that ſhalbe of
.xl. mynutes &amp; no mo. Thus in De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cembre the temporall houres of the daye haue but .xl. mynutes / but the houres of the nyghte haue .lxxx. For in that tyme the nyghtꝭ haue .xvi. houres artyfycyalles / the whiche deuy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in
.xii. partyes / ben .lxxx. mynutes for eue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry temporall houre. Thus the houre of the ny<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ghtes in Decembre haue .lxxx. mynutes &amp; .xl. For an houre of the daye is .vi. ſcore mynutes in two temporal houres / as many as in two houres artyfycyalles / that ben eche of .xl. my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nutes in Iune is the contrary: in Marche and
<pb facs="tcp:15753:45"/> in Septembre al houres ben egall / as the day<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>es ben in other monethes by egall porcyon.</p>
                  <p>¶ with euery planette here before named ben the ſygnes
/ whiche ben the houſes of the ſayd planettes / as it is beforeſayd. Capricornus &amp; Aquarius ben the houſes of Saturne. Sagit tarius and Piſces / of Iupiter. Scorpius and Aries of Mars. Leo of Sol. Taurus and Li<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bra of Venꝰ. Gemini of Mercury. And Can<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cer of Luna / with other ſygnyfycacions that wolde be longe to recounte.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="40" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ Alſo hereafter foloweth the Natures of the .vii. Planettes / with theyr dyſpoſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyons / after the ſayinge of Ptholome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us / prynce of Aſtronomy. Cap<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> .xl.</head>
               <div n="Saturn" type="planet">
                  <head>¶ The firſte planet is Saturne.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Aturne is the hyeſt Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net of all the .vii. he is my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghty of hym ſelf: he gyueth all the great coldes &amp; wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters / yet he is drye &amp; colde of nature / and he cometh in to Cancer: and his chefe ſygnes ben Aquarius and Capricornus: and he compaſſeth al the other planettes. For Sa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>turne is nexte vnder the firſte mobyle that is
<pb facs="tcp:15753:46"/> vnder the cryſtall ſkye / the whiche mobyle moueth meruaylouſly / for ſome Aſtronomy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers ſaye / that he cauſeth by his mouynge all other planettes to moue / and moueth the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byle aboue. Saturne is ſo hye that Aſtrono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myers can nat well meſure it. For ſo hye rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon hathe power and no ferther / and therfore it is more than .xxx. yere or he may ronne his courſe. whan he dothe reygne / there is moche thefte vſed / and lytell charyte / moche lyinge / and moche lawynge one agaynſt another / &amp; and great pryſonynge / and moche debate / &amp; great ſwerynge. And moche plente of corne / and alſo moche plente of hogges / and great trauayle on the erthe / and olde folke ſhall be very ſyckely: and many dyſeaſes ſhal reygne amonge the people / and ſpecyally in the chefe houres of Saturne / And therfore this planet is lykened vnto age / as harde / hungry / ſuſpe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyous / and couetous / that ſelden is content with any thynge / for Saturne is ennemy to all thyngꝭ / that growe &amp; bere lyfe of natuer / for the colde &amp; ſtormy bytternes of his tyme.</p>
                  <div type="properties">
                     <head>¶ The proprytes of Saturne.</head>
                     <p>THe man that is borne vnder Saturne ſhall be falſe / enuyous / and full of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate / and full of lawe / and he ſhal be cunnynge in coryenge of lether / &amp; a great eter
<pb facs="tcp:15753:46"/> of brede and fleſſhe / and he ſhall haue a ſtyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kynge breth: and he ſhall be heuy / thoughtfull and malycyous / a robber / a fyghter / and full of couetous / and yet he ſhall kepe well coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyle / and be wyſe in counceylynge / &amp; he ſhal loue to ſynne wylfully / he ſhal be a great ſpe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ker of tales / Iuſtes / &amp; Cronycles
/ and ſhall haue lytel iyen / blacke heer / great lyppes / bro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de ſholdres
/ and ſhall loke downewarde. He ſhall nat loue Sermons / nor go to the chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che / and beware of his handes: &amp; he beholdeth the mylte / &amp; aboue his neres the planet dothe reygne. And the children of the ſayd Saturne ſhall be great Iangelers and chyders / blacke and lene in the face / thyn berded / euyl langua<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ged / &amp; ſhall be full of lawe and vengeaunce And they wyll neuer forgyue tyll they be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenged of theyr quarell / and lyke as the pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net Saturne is colde / and cauſer of great fro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtes and ſnowes / ſemblably he that is borne vnder hym ſhall be colde in charyte / and nat myſericordyous and mercyfull / but vengea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble / &amp; wyll neuer be entreated. And alſo they ſhall be great curſers / and bere malyce longe in theyr myndes and nat forgyue it / and they loke to be obeyed and to haue great reuerence: and comonly wyll prayſe them ſelfe and tal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke to them ſelfe / &amp; laughe at theyr owne con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyte
<pb facs="tcp:15753:47"/> / and all euyll ſhall growe in them / and aboue all coloures he ſhal loue blacke coloure beſte. The planet of Saturne gouerneth of man the mylte / and aboue the neres as is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſayd / &amp; this planet is cauſe of haſty dethe / for bycauſe that he is drye and colde of natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re / And therfore he is lykened to melancoly. And the ſayd Saturne reygneth in Aquary / Caprycorne / and Cancer / but ſpecyally in Aquary and Caprycorne.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="Jupiter" type="planet">
                  <head>¶ Secondely of the noble Planet Iupiter.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>Vpiter the noble Planet is very pure &amp; clere of nature / and nat very hote / but he is all vertuous. And there is fyxed in Iupiter two noble Sygnes of loue / the one is Piſces / and the other is Sagittary: ſygnes of none euyll / nor of none vnhapynes / this pla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>net maye nat do none euyll / he is beſte of all the other / he kepeth the lyuer of man: &amp; mayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayneth it ioyouſly / and euermore this planet dothe alwayes good &amp; none euyll / and with in .xii. yere or there aboute / he paſſeth all the
.xii. ſygnes. And he is next after Saturne.</p>
                  <div type="properties">
                     <pb facs="tcp:15753:47"/>
                     <head>¶ The proprytes of Iupiter</head>
                     <p>HE that is borne vnder hym ſhall loue clenlynes of body / and wyll nat vſe to ſpeke of rybaudry / and harlottry / he ſhall euer loue relygyon / and vertuous ly<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uynge / he ſhall be perſonable of body / he ſhal be perfyte in all maner of meaſures bothe lar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge and longe / he ſhall be whyte in the vyſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge / medled with a lytell rednes / large brow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es
/ he ſhall be a fayre ſpeker / and ſay well be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>hynde a perſone / he ſhall loue grene coloure &amp; graye / he ſhall be happy in marchaundyſe
/ &amp; haue plente of golde &amp; ſyluer / &amp; he ſhall loue to ſynge and to be honeſtly mery. And of the man he gouerneth the ſtomacke &amp; the armes.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="Mars" type="planet">
                  <head>¶ Thyrdly of Mars.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Ars is called the god of batay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>le and of warre / and he is the thyrde planet / for he reygneth next vnder the gentyll planet of Iupiter. This planet Mars is the worſte of all other / for he is hote &amp; drye / and ſtyreth a man to be very wylful &amp; ſtaſty lyghtly / and to vnhappynes
/ one of his ſyg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes is Aries / and the other Scorpio / &amp; moſte he is in thoſe two ſygnes. He cauſeth all war<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes
<pb facs="tcp:15753:48"/> and bataylles / this planet ſtyreth men to bere wepons / as murderers / daggers / ſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des / bylles / or bowes / or ſome other wepon of dethe / and wolde euer here of fyghtynge. Therfore let euery man be ware of the dayes of Mars / and in his chefe houres that no man fyghte / for without doubte if god helpe hym nat / he ſhal be maymed or ſlayne. Alſo in the houres of Mars is peryllous metynge with theues / for drede of ſleynge of true men. And Saturne mounteth in to the Crabbe / &amp; gothe aboute the
.xii. ſygnes in two yere / and thus he ronneth his courſe.</p>
                  <div type="properties">
                     <head>¶ The proprytes of Mars.</head>
                     <p>HE that is borne vnder this Planet of Mars / in all vnhappynes is experte / he ſhall be a nouryſſher of great beeſtꝭ he is full of malyce / and euer doynge wron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge. Vnder Mars is borne theues and robbers that kepe hye wayes / &amp; do hurte to true men / and nyght walkers / quarell pykers / boſters / mockers / &amp; ſkoffers / and theſe men of Mars cauſeth warre and murther / &amp; batayle / they wyll be gladly ſmythes or workers on yron lyght fyngred / and lyers &amp; great ſwerers of othes in ve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geable wyſe: &amp; a great ſurmyler &amp; crafty / he is red and angry with blacke heer / and lytell iyen / he ſhall be a great walker / &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:15753:48"/> a maker of ſwordes and knyues / and a ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes blode / a fornycatour / and a ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker of rybawdry / red berded / rounde vyſage: and good to be a barboure and a blode letter / and to drawe tethe / &amp; is peryllous of his han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des / and he wyll be ryche with other mennes gooddes. And of the body of man Mars ke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth the galle and the reynes.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="Sun" type="planet">
                  <head>¶ Fourthly of the noble planet Sol.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S for Sol is a Planet of great renowne / and kyng of all the planettes / for the Sonne nouryſſheth euery age / and yet is he hote and drye of nature / and the pla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>net of Saturne is to hym full contrary: for he is euer colde / &amp; the noble planet of the Sonne is hote / and gyueth all lyght. For whan it is aboue the erthe it is day / and whan the erthe dothe ſhadowe the Sonne / it is nyght moche be we both man and woman bounde to lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de god for this noble planet: for he comforteth bothe man and beeſt / fyſſes / and all fowles that flyen in the ayre / all thynges ben gladde of the Sonne / after that the ſonne gothe in to the weſt / the fayre floures cloſe them ſelfe.</p>
                  <div type="properties">
                     <pb facs="tcp:15753:49"/>
                     <head>¶ The proprytes of the noble planet Sol:</head>
                     <p>KYnge of all the planettes is Sol / All men and women that ben borne vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der this planette of Sol ſhall be very fayre / amyable of face / and theyr ſkynne ſhal be right whyte and tender / and wel coloured in the vyſage with a lytell rednes / and they ſhall haue a pleaſure in theyr owne beaute / and they ſhal ſhewe theyr lyues as they were good and holy / but they ſhal be ſecrete ypocry<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes if they gyue them to relygyon / they ſhal be fortunate to great promocyons / they ſhall be clene and good of fayth / and ſhall be gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noure of other people / and if they be neuer ſo poore / yet ſhall they loue hawkynge and hun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tynge / with houndes and hawkes
/ and reioy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce to ſe it / The children that be borne vnder the Sonne ſhall deſyre honoure and ſcyence / and ſhall ſynge very pleaſauntly / and they ſhall be full of courage good and dylygent / &amp; ſhall deſyre lordſhyp aboue other people / they ſhall gyue wyſe Iugementꝭ / and theyr wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des ſhall ſounde all ſwetely / &amp; if he bere any offyce he ſhall be lyberall / and he ſhall be ſub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyll in dedes of warre / and many ſhal ſeke to hym for cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceyle / he ſhall haue profyte by wo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>men / and he ſhall be in ſeruyce with lordes / &amp; by them ſhal haue auau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tage for his wyſdom:
<pb facs="tcp:15753:49"/> his ſygne ſhall be in the face / he ſhall be ſmall of ſtature / with ſcrype heer and balde on the heed / he wyll be ſeldon angry / and of all the membres in mannes body the Sonne kepeth the herte / as moſte myghtyeſt planet about all the other planettes.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="Venus" type="planet">
                  <head>¶ Fyfthly of the gentyll Planet Venus.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">V</seg>Enus the gentyll planet reyg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth next after the ſon<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e / and is a planet femynyne / and is a la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy ouer all louers / this planet is moyſte and colde of nature / and her two ſygnes ben Taurus and Libra and in them ſhe hathe all her Ioye and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaunce / ſhe cauſeth Ioye / &amp; ſpecyally amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge yonge folke / for greatly ſhe reygneth on them and on all men that ben Ialous / and wome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> alſo / for Ialouſy is but a loue inordynat
/ as whan a man or a woman loueth more fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uently than they ſhuld: for ſuche wolde neuer be from the ſyght of theyr louers: for if they be anone they ſuſpecte them and drede for fere to be begyled. For there is no man that loueth a woman by carnall affeccion / but it is by the influence of Venus
/ and but fewe men can
<pb facs="tcp:15753:50"/> eſcape out of her dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger. This planet Venus reygneth in .xii. monthes ouer the .xii. ſygnes.</p>
                  <div type="properties">
                     <head>¶ The proprytes of Venus.</head>
                     <p>ALl theſe men &amp; women / that ben borne vnder Venus / they ſhall be very gaye louers / pleaſaunt and delycyous / and moſte comonly they ſhall haue blacke iyen / &amp; lytell browes / red lyppes and chekes / with a ſmylynge chere / they ſhall loue the noyſe of trumpettes
/ claryons / and of other mynſtral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy / and they ſhall be pleaſaunt ſyngers with ſwete voyces / &amp; full of wanton toyes / play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es / and ſkoffynges / and ſhall greatly delyte in daunſynge / &amp; in caſtynge of gamboudes / with lepynge and ſpryngynge / &amp; wyll vſe playinge at the cheſſe / cardes / &amp; tables / &amp; deſy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re oft to comen of luſte &amp; loue / &amp; coueyte often ſwete metes &amp; drynkes / as wyne / &amp; be often dronken / &amp; deſyre lechery / and the beholdynge of fayre women / and the women of men in lyke wyſe. And vſe the dede of fleſſhely luſte often tymes: they wyll deſyre fayre clothes of gay coloure and fyne / with rynges of vany<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te / &amp; all vayne pleaſure of the worlde / with perles &amp; precyous ſtones / they ſhall loue flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res with ſwete ſmelles / yet ſhall they be of good fayth: and they ſhall loue other as well as them ſelfe / &amp; they ſhall be lyberall to theyr
<pb facs="tcp:15753:50"/> frendes / they ſhal haue fewe enemyes / if they be browne / they ſhall be well proporcyoned of body / and if they ſwere it is true / ye maye byleue them / and Venus gouerneth the kyd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neys of man.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="Mercury" type="planet">
                  <head>¶ Syxtely of the fayre planet Mercury.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Eercury the fayre planette / is next vnder Venus / &amp; is maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culyne next aboue the Mone / This Mercury is very full &amp; drye of nature: &amp; his two pryn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cypall ſygnes ben theſe / Gemini is the firſte that reygneth in the armes / and in the han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of man or woman / &amp; the other ſygne is Virgo that gouerneth the nauyll and the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macke of man / this planet is Lorde of ſpeche in lykewyſe as the Sonne is lorde of lyghte. This planet Mercury paſſeth &amp; cyrcuyte the .xii. ſygnes / in .CCC. &amp; xxx viii. dayes.</p>
                  <div type="properties">
                     <head>¶ The proprytes of Mercury.</head>
                     <p>WHo ſo is borne vnder Mercury ſhalbe very ſubtyll of wyt / and ſhal be a de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uoute perſone to god / and haue good conſcy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence / and ſhall be very crafty in many ſcyen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces / he with his wyſdom and laboure ſhall gette hym many frendes and louers. He ſhall
<pb facs="tcp:15753:51"/> euer folowe &amp; reſorte to them that be of good maners / &amp; ſhall be fortunate on the ſee to vſe the courſe of marchaundyſe / he ſhall be very gracyous / he ſhall haue harme by women / &amp; whan he is maryed men ſhall nat ſette ſo mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che by hym as they dyd before / he wyll haue great loue to ladyes and gentyl women / but yet they ſhall nat be mayſters ouer hym / he wyll be a very good man of the churche
/ or a relygyous man / and he ſhall nat loue to go a warre fare / he wyll hate theues &amp; ſwerers / &amp; he ſhall gather great goodes by his wyſdom. If he be a man of the worlde he ſhall be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyte in ſome hande crafte / he ſhall loue well to preche: and to ſpeke fayre rethoryke langua<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge / and to talke of Phyloſophy &amp; geometry / he ſhall loue well wrytynge &amp; to rede euer in ſtraunge bokes / &amp; to caſte accomptes of great nombres / and ſhall be a great maker of bala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des / ſonges / metres / and rymes / he ſhal be per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fyte in the arte of muſyke and loue it / he ſhall loue meſurynge &amp; metynge / and ſhal be ſome great clothe maker / he ſhal be ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to ſome great lorde / or ellys a receyuer of his money / he ſhall haue a hye foreheed / a longe vyſage / black iyen / &amp; a thyn berde / he ſhall be a great pleder in the lawe / and he wyll medle with other mennes dedes / and they do nat well &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:15753:51"/> ſaye agaynſt it / and Mercury gouerneth the thyghes / the bely / and the flankes.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="Moon" type="planet">
                  <head>¶ Seuenthly of the Mone.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S it is knowen and to be vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de / that the low<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eſt planet of the .vii .is na<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>med Luna / the which we call the mone / the whiche planet is called feminyne or female / and is called amonge Aſtronomy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ers the Lady of the nyght / for the chefe lyghte and clerenes that is by nyght / is by the preſen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce of the mone / for the mone is moche more ne<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rer approched vnto vs than any fterre is / &amp; therfore ſhe gyueth vs moch more lyght than the ſterres dothe / and alſo the mone is lady of moyſture: and ruleth the ſee by ebbe and ſtore the mone doth take her lyght of the ſon<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e .xxii. tymes in the yere. And alſo the mone is colde and moyſte of nature / and her coloure is mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che fayrer than ſyluer / and her chefe howſe is Cancer / and there is none of the other planet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes that be ſo lowe / and goth ſo lytel cyrcuyte as doth the Mone / and deſcendeth in to Scor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pio / And ſhe gothe aboute the .xii. ſygnes in .xxvi. dayes / and than chaungeth and recal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
<pb facs="tcp:15753:52"/> newe. And this is the courſe of the Mone: after the ſayinge of Ptholomeus.</p>
                  <div type="properties">
                     <head>¶ The propretes of Luna.</head>
                     <p>SVche men and women as ben borne vnder the Mone ſhall be lowly and ſeruyable / and very gentyll. And if it be a mayden childe / ſhe ſhal be very ſhame faſte and womanly / and they ſhall be well fauoured both man and woman / theyr faces ſhall be full &amp; rounde / they ſhall be very pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyent folkes: and wyll ſuffre moche wronge or they be reuenged / and wyll be ſofte of ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che and very curteyſe / and ſhall lyue honſtly with ſuche as god ſhal ſende them / and wyl haunte vertuous company / they ſhal be wel fourmed of body: and haue mery lokes &amp; loue honeſtly to be glad / &amp; wyll lyue very chaſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly / &amp; loue greatly the vertue of clennes / bothe in worde &amp; dede / they hate lecherous talkers / of rybawdry / theyr colour ſhal be myxed but with lytell rednes / they ſhal ryght gladly go arayed in many coloured clothes / &amp; they ſhall ſoone ſwete in the forhed. Alſo they wyll ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue great deſyre to be mayſters &amp; mayſtreſſes ouer great ſtremes / ryuers / and floodes / and ſhall deuyſe many propre engynes for to take fyſſhe &amp; to deceyue them / loke what they ſaye and it ſhall be true &amp; ſtedfaſte / and they ſhall
<pb facs="tcp:15753:52"/> be very honeſt &amp; good goers on fote: and wyl comforte ſycke perſons / he ſhall loue wel to talke ſomtyme of meruayles / he ſhall nat ke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe hatred longe in his mynde / and he ſhall ap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>peſe the people vnder colour with co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munyca<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyons: as well as other ſhuld do with ſyluer. Honeſt women he ſhall loue / &amp; he wyll hate harlottes &amp; brothelles / and ſhall noryſſhe chil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dren vp in vertu and good maners. And the lyghtes and the braynes of man is vnder the gouernaunce of Luna that is the moone.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="41" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ Thus endeth the .vii. Planettes with theyr proprytes. And here foloweth / to knowe the Fortunes and deſtenyes of man and woman borne vnder the .xii. Sygnes (after the ſayinge of Ptholomeus) prynce of Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomye. Capitulo .xli.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>O to know vnder what planet a man or woman is borne / It is nedefull to wete that there is .vii. pla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nettes on the ſkye / that is to ſay / Sol / Venꝰ / Mars Mercurius / Iupiter / Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na / and Saturnus. Of the .vii. Planettes is
<pb facs="tcp:15753:53"/> named the .vii. dayes of the weke / for euery daye hath his name of the Planet reygnynge in the begynnynge of it. The auncyent Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers ſaye that Sol domyneth the Son<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day (the cauſe is they ſay) for the Sonne amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge other planettes is moſte worthy: wherfore it taketh the worthyeſt daye / that is the ſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day. Luna domyneth the firſte houre of mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day. Mars the firſte houre of tewyſday. Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curius for wednyſday. Iupiter for thurſday. Venus for fryday / And Saturnus for ſater<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>day. The day naturall hathe .xxiiii. houres / &amp; euery houre reygneth a planet. ¶ It is for to be noted that whan a man wyll begyn to re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ken at ſonday / he muſte reken thus / Sol / Ve<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nus / Mercurius / Luna / Saturnus / Iupiter / Mars. And whan the nombre is fayled / he muſt begyn at the houre that he wold know what planet reygneth. The mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>day he ought to begyn at Luna. The tewyſday at Mars. The wednyſday at Mercury. The thurſday at Iupiter. The fryday at Venus. The ſater<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>day at Saturnus. And euer whan the nom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bres of the planettes is fayled / he muſt begyn by ordre as is aforeſayd. ¶ Alſo it is to be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted that the Grekes do begyn theyr day in the mornynge. The Iewes at noone. And the Cryſten men at mydnyght: &amp; there we ought
<pb facs="tcp:15753:53"/> lo begyn to reken. For at one of the clocke on Sonday in the mornynge reygneth Sol / at .ii. reygneth Venus / at .iii. reygneth Mercury / at .iiii. reygneth Luna / at .v. Saturne / at .vi. Iupiter / at .vii. Mars / and at .viii. begynne agayne at Sol / at .iv. Venus / at .v. Mercury / at .vi. Luna / at .vii. Saturne: and ſo by ordre in euery houre. ¶ whan a childe is borne / it is to be knowen at what houre / and if it be in the begynnynge of the houre / in the myddes / or at the ende. If it be in the begynnynge / he ſhal holde of the ſame planet / and of the other before. If it be in the myddes / it ſhall holde of that onely. If it be borne in the ende / it ſhall holde of the ſame / &amp; of that that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth nexte after: Neuertheleſſe the planet that it is borne vnder ſhall nat rule other / &amp; that of the daye ſhall be aboue it / whiche is the cauſe that a childe holdeth of dyuers planettes / and hathe dyuers condycions. ¶ He that is borne vnder Sol ſhall be prudent and wyſe &amp; a great ſpe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ker / &amp; that whiche he prayſeth he holdeth ver<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tuous in hym ſelf. ¶ who that is born vnder Venus is loued of euery man / good to god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde and reguler. ¶ who that is borne vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der Mercury is well berded / ſubtyll / mylde / verytable / and is nat moſte prudent. ¶ who that is born vnder Luna hath an hye forehed
<pb facs="tcp:15753:54"/> ruddy / mery vyſage / ſhamefaſt / &amp; relygious, ¶ who that is borne vnder Saturne is har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy / curteyſe of lyuynge / &amp; is nat auarycyous. ¶ who that is borne vnder Iupiter is hardy fayre vyſage &amp; ruddy / chaſte &amp; vagabounde. ¶ who that is borne vnder Mars / is a great ſpeker / a lyer / a thefe / a deceyuer / bygge &amp; of reed colour. ¶ They that wyl knowe of this more euydently / let them tourne to the propry<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes of the .vii. planettes before reherſed.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="42" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ The prologue of Ptholomeus vpon the .xii. ſygnes. Capitulo .xlii.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Conſyderynge the courſe of the celeſtiall bodyes: and the power of the hye god omny<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>potent / the whiche hath ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de the ſonne to ſhyne vpon the good and euyll / that go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerneth all thynges conteyned in the Fyrma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment / and on the erthe haue taken vpon me for to endyte this lytell treatyſe / for to inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ete &amp; endoctryne the people nat lettred. Firſte to knowe god theyr maker. Secondely to go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerne theyr bodyes / and eſchewe infyrmytes. And thyrdely to knowe the courſe of the fyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mament / and of the celeſtyall bodyes contey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb facs="tcp:15753:54"/> in it / with the diſpoſicions of the .vii. pla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nettes. But who that wyll knowe his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prytes ought firſte to knowe the Moneth that he was borne in: and the ſygne that the ſonne was in the ſame daye. I wyll nat ſaye that ſuche thynges ſhall be / but that the ſygnes ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue ſuche proprytes / as it is the wyll of god. After Poetes and Aſtronomyers / Aries is the firſte ſygne that ſheweth the Fortunes of men and women / as ſayth Ptholomeus.</p>
               <div n="Aries" type="zodiac_sign">
                  <head>¶ The firſte ſygne is Aries. Good to let blode.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Ere is to be knowen that he which is borne in the ſy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gne of Aries: from mydde Marche to mydde Apryll ſhall be of good wytte / &amp; ſhall nouther be ryche nor poore: he ſhall haue doma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge by his neyghboures
/ he ſhall haue power ouer deed folkes goodes / he ſhall be ſoone an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry
/ and ſoone appeſed / he ſhall haue dyuers fortunes and diſcordes / he wyll deſyre doctry<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne / and haunte eloquent people / and ſhall be experte in many degrees / he ſhall be a lyer &amp; vnſtedfaſte of courage / and wyll take ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geaunce
<pb facs="tcp:15753:55"/> on his enemyes / and he ſhal be better dyſpoſed in youthe in all thyngꝭ than in age / vnto .xxxiii. he ſhall be a forny catour / &amp; ſhal be wedded at .xxv. yere &amp; if he be nat / he ſhal nat be chaſte / he ſhal be a medyatour for ſome of his frendes / and wyl gladly be beſy in the nedes of other / he ſhall be wayted to be doma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ged / he ſhal haue a ſygne in the ſholder / in his hed / &amp; in his body / yet he ſhall be ryche by the dethe of other / his firſte ſone ſhal nat lyue lon<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge / he ſhall be in dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger of .iiii. foted beſtes / he ſhall haue great ſyckenes at .xxiii. yere: &amp; if he eſcape he ſhal lyue .lxxxv. yere after nature.</p>
                  <div n="female" type="character">
                     <head>¶ The woman.</head>
                     <p>THe woman that is borne in this tyme ſhal be yrefull and ſuffre great wron<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges from daye to day / ſhe wyll gladly make leſynges / and ſhall loſe her huſbande &amp; recouer a better / ſhe ſhall be ſycke at .v. yere of age / and at .xxv. ſhe ſhall be in great dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger of deth / And if ſhe eſcape ſhe ſhal be in doubte<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyll .xliii. yere: and ſhall ſuffre great payne in the hed. The dayes of Sol &amp; of Mars to them ſhall be ryght good / and the dayes of Iupiter ſhal be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary to them. And as well the man as the woman may be ſemblable to the ſhepe that euery yere loſeth his fleſe / &amp; within ſhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te ſpace getteth it agayne.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="Taurus" type="zodiac_sign">
                  <pb facs="tcp:15753:55"/>
                  <head>¶ Of the ſygne of Taurus. Euyll to let blode.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He man that is born in the ſygne of Taurus / from myd Apryll to myd Maye / ſhall be ſtronge / har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy / and full of ſtryfe / delycyous / and ſhall poſſede goodes gyuen to hym by other men / that he wold haue done ſhall be done incontynent / and wyll enforce hym ſelfe to fynyſſhe it. In his youth he wyl dyſpyſe euery perſone / and ſhal be yrefull / he ſhall go pylgrymages and wyll leue his fren<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des &amp; lyue amonge ſtraungers he ſhal be put in offyces / and ſhall excercyſe them well / &amp; ſhal be ryche by women / he ſhal be thankeles and come to good eſtate / he wyll take venge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>aunce on his enemyes / he ſhall be bytten of a dogge / and ſhall experyme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t many paynes by women / and ſhal be in peryll at .xxxiii. yere / he ſhal be in peryll of water / and ſhal be gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued with ſyckenes and venym at .xxiii. yere: and at .xxx. yere he ſhal be habundaunt in ry<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cheſſe / and ſhall ryſe to great dygnyte / &amp; ſhall lyue
.lxxxv. yere and .iii. monthes after natu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re: and ſhall ſe his fortune ſorowfull.</p>
                  <p>WE ſe the woman that is borne in this tyme ſhal be effectuall / labrourynge / and a great lyer / and ſhall ſuffre moche ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me
<pb facs="tcp:15753:56"/> / ſhe ſhall reioyce the goodes of her frendes the whiche ſhe conceyueth in her mynde ſhall come to effecte / and ſhal haue the beſte partye ſhe ſhall haue many huſbandes / &amp; many chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren / ſhe ſhal be in her beſte eſtate at .xvi. yere and ſhe ſhall haue a ſygne in the myddes of her body / ſhe ſhal be ſyckely / and if ſhe eſcape ſhe ſhall lyue .lxxvi. yere after nature. She ought to bere rynges &amp; precyous ſtones about her. The dayes of Iupiter and Luna be right good for them / &amp; the dayes of Mars be contra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry / as well the man as the woman maye be lykened to the Gull that laboureth the lande and whan the ſede is ſowen he hathe but the ſtrawe for his parte / they ſhal kepe wel theyr owne / and it ſhall nat profyte to them nor to other / and ſhal be reputed vnkynde.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="Gemini" type="zodiac_sign">
                  <head>¶ Of the ſygne of Gemini. Euyll to let blode.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>E that is borne in the ſygne of Gemini / from myd Maye to myd Iune / ſhall haue many woundes / &amp; he ſhall be fayne and mercyfull
/ he ſhal lede an open &amp; a reſonable lyfe / he ſhal receyue moche money / he wyll go in vnknowen places / &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:15753:56"/> do many pylgrymages / he wyll prayſe hym ſelf &amp; wyll nat abyde in the place of his naty<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uyte / he ſhal be wyſe &amp; neclygent in his wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes / he ſhall come to ryches at .xxvi. yere / his firſte wyfe ſhall nat lyue longe / but he ſhall mary ſtrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge women / he ſhal be late maryed he ſhal be bytten of a dogge / and ſhall haue a marke of yron or of fyre / he ſhal be tourme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted in water / &amp; ſhall paſſe the ſee / and ſhall lyue an .C. yere / and .x. monthes after nature.</p>
                  <p>THe woman than borne / ſhall come to honoure / and be ſet forward with the goodes of other / and ſhe ſhal be a gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued of a falſe cryme / ſhe ought to be wedded at .xiiii. yere / if ſhe ſhal be chaſte and eſchewe all peryll / and ſhall lyue .lxx. yere after natu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re / and ſhall honoure god. The dayes of Mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cury &amp; Sol to them be right good: the dayes of Luna and Venus ben to them contrary / and as well the man as the woman ſhall auge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and aſſemble the goodes of theyr ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſoures / but ſcantly ſhall they vſe theyr owne goodes / they ſhal be ſo auarycyous.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="Cancer" type="zodiac_sign">
                  <head>¶ Of the ſygne of Cancer. Indifferent to let blode.</head>
                  <p>HE that is borne vnder the Sygne of Cancer / from myd Iune to myd Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="tcp:15753:57"/> / ſhal be very auarycyous and of egall ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture / he wyll loue women / he ſhall be mery / humble / good / and well renowmed / he ſhall haue domage by enuye / he ſhall haue money of other in his guyde / he ſhal be a conductour of other folkes thyngꝭ / he ſhall haue ſtryfe &amp; diſcorde amonge his neyghboures / and wyll auenge hym on his enemye by his ſtatelynes many ſhall mocke hym / he ſhall haue often great fere on the water / he wyll kepe his cou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rage ſecretely in hym ſelfe
/ and ſhal ſuffre do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loure of the wombe / he ſhal fynde hydden mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ney / and laboure ſore for his wyfe / he ſhall ſe his peryll in a certayne yere
/ the whiche ſhall be knowen of god / his goodes ſhall decreaſe at
.xxxiii. yere / he ſhall paſſe the ſee / and ſhal lyue .lxx. yere after nature / and forture ſhall be agreable to hym.</p>
                  <p>THe woman that ſhall be borne in this tyme ſhal be furyous
/ incontynent an<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gry and ſoone appeſed / ſhe is nymble / ſeruyable / wyſe / mery: &amp; ſhe ſhall ſuffre right many perylles / if any perſone do her any ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyſe ſhe wyll recompence them well: ſhe ſhal be labouryng &amp; take great payne vnto .xxx. yere / and than ſhall haue reſte / ſhe ſhall haue many ſones / ſhe muſte be wedded at .xiiii. ye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re honoures and gyftes ſhall folowe her / ſhe
<pb facs="tcp:15753:57"/> ſhall haue woundes and be hole therof / &amp; ſhe ſhal be in peryll of waters: &amp; ſhe ſhal be hurte in a ſecrete place / ſhe ſhal be bytten of a dogge and ſhe ſhall lyue .lxx. yere after nature. The dayes of Iupiter / Venus / and Luna: to them ben right good / and the dayes of Mars ryght euyll / &amp; as well the man as the woman ſhal haue good fortune / and ſhall haue victorye ouer theyr enemyes.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="Leo" type="zodiac_sign">
                  <head>¶ Of the ſygne of Leo. Euyll to let blode.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Ertayne he that is borne vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der the Sygne of Leo / from myd Iuly to myd Auguſt / ſhall be fayne and hardy / he ſhall ſpeke openly / &amp; ſhal be mercyfull / and he ſhal wepe with the wepers / and ſhal be ſtately in wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des / he ſhall haue a peryll in certayne tyme / &amp; at
.xxx. yere he ſhall be awayted to be doma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged / but he ſhall eſchewe that peryll / his bene<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fyces ſhal be vnkynde: he ſhal be honoured of good folke
/ &amp; obtayne his enterpryſe / he ſhall haue goodes by temporall ſeruyces / he ſhal be vnkynde to theues / &amp; ſhal be great &amp; puyſau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t he ſhall haue charge of the comonte / &amp; as mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che
<pb facs="tcp:15753:58"/> as loſeth he ſhall wynne / he ſhall come to dygnyte &amp; ſhal be amyable / he ſhall take the fortune of thre wyues / he wyll go often on pylgrymages / and ſuffre payne of the ſyght / he ſhal fall from hye and be ferefull of water he ſhall fynde hyd money at .viii. yere of age / he ſhal be ſycke / he ſhal be in peryl and doubte of ſome great Lorde / &amp; at .xxxvi. yere he ſhal be bytten of a dogge / and be hole with great payne / &amp; ſhall lyue .lxxxiiii. yere aft<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nature.</p>
                  <p>THe woman that is borne in this tyme ſhal be a great lyer / fayre / wel ſpoken mercyfull / pleaſau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t / &amp; may nat ſuffre norſe men wepe / ſhe ſhall be meke / her firſte huſbande ſhall nat lyue longe / ſhe ſhall haue payne in her ſtomacke: ſhe ſhal be awayted of her neyghboures at .xvii. yere / &amp; lyue to great rycheſſe / ſhe ſhall haue chyldren of thre men / ſhe ſhal be amyable and haue the blody flyxe and ſhal be bytten of a dogge / ſhe ſhall falle from hye / and lyue
.lxxvii. yere after nature. The dayes of Mercury / Sol / &amp; Mars to them be ryght good / the dayes of Saturne ben con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trary / &amp; as well the man as the woman ſhal be hardy &amp; great quaryllers &amp; mercyfull.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="Virgo" type="zodiac_sign">
                  <head>¶ Of the ſygne of Virgo. Indifferent to let beode.</head>
                  <p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:15753:58"/> 
                     <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>F the ſygne of Virgo / I fyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de that he whiche is borne fro myd Auguſt to myd Septem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bre ſhall gladly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mende his wyfe / he ſhal be a great houſe holder engenyous / he ſhal be ſolycitous to his worke / he ſhal be ſhamefaſt and of great cou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rage / and all that he ſeth he ſhall coueyt in his vnderſtandynge / he wyll be ſoone angry / &amp; ſurmount his enemyes. Scarſly ſhall he be a whyle with his firſte wyſe / he ſhal be fortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate at .xxxi. yere / he wyll nat hyde that he hath / &amp; ſhal be in peryll of water / he ſhall ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue a wounde with yron / and ſhall lyue .lxx. yere after nature.</p>
                  <p>SHe that than is borne ſhall be ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſte / engenyous
/ &amp; wyll take payne and ſhe ought to be wedded at .xii. ye<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re / ſhe ſhall nat be longe with her firſt huſba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de. Her ſeconde huſbande ſhal be of longe ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe: and ſhall haue moche good by another wo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>man / ſhe ſhal fall from hye / her lyfe ſhal be in peryll and ſhall dye ſhortely
/ ſhe ſhall ſuffer doloure at .x. yere / if ſhe eſcape that doloures
/ ſhe ſhall lyue .lxx. yere after nature / ſhe ſhall brynge forthe vertuous fruyte / &amp; euery thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge ſhall fauoure her: ſhe ſhal reioyce in dyuers fortunes. The dayes of Mercury and of Sol
<pb facs="tcp:15753:59"/> ſhal be ryght good for them / and the dayes of Mars ſhal be contrary. And as wel the man as the woman ſhall ſuffer many temptacy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons / ſo that with great payne they may reſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſte them / they ſhall delyte to lyue chaſte / but they ſhall ſuffer moche where that it be.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="Libra" type="zodiac_sign">
                  <head>¶ Of the ſygne of Libra. Good to let blode.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Et amonge the Planettes Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bra ought to be remembred / for he that is borne from myd Sep<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tembre to myd Octobre he ſhal be right myghtely prayſed and honoured in the ſeruyce of cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taynes / he ſhal go in vnknowen places / and ſhall gette in ſtraunge landes / he ſhall kepe well his owne / if he make nat reuolucion by drynke he wyll nat kepe his promeſſe: he ſhal be enuyed by ſyluer &amp; other goodes / he ſhal be maryed and go from his wyfe / he ſhall ſpeke quyckely and haue noo domage amonge his neyghboures / he ſhall haue vnder his myght the goodes of deed folke / and ſhall haue ſome ſygne in his membres. Oxen / horſe / and other beſtes ſhal be gyuen to hym / he ſhall haue do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage and imury / he ſhal be enryched by wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men
<pb facs="tcp:15753:59"/> / and experyment euyll fortunes / many ſhall aſke counceyle of hym. And he ſhall ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue .lxx. yere after nature.</p>
                  <p>THe woman that is borne in this tyme ſhal be amyable and of great courage ſhe wyll announce the deth of her ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myes: and ſhall go in places vnknowen / ſhe ſhal be debonayre &amp; mery / and reioyce by her huſbande / if ſhe be nat wedded at .xiii. yere ſhe ſhall nat be chaſte / and ſhal haue no ſones by her firſte huſbande / ſhe ſhall go many pyl<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>grymages / after .xxx. yere ſhe ſhall proſpere in better / and haue great honoure and prayſe: than after ſhe ſhal be greuouſly ſycke / &amp; ſhall be brent in the fete aboue .xii. yere of age / and ſhall lyue .lx. yere after nature. The dayes of Venue and of Luna for them ben right good and the dayes of Mercucy contrary. And as well the man as the woman ſhall be in dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bte vnto theyr dethe.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="Scorpio" type="zodiac_sign">
                  <head>¶ Of the ſygne of Scorpio. Good to let blode.</head>
                  <p>HE whiche is borne i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſygne of Scor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pius / from myd Octobre to myd No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uembre ſhal haue good fortune: he ſhal be a great fornycatour. The firſte wyfe that
<pb facs="tcp:15753:60"/> he ſhall haue in maryage ſhall become relygy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ous / he wyll ſerue gladly to ymages / he ſhall ſuffer payne in his pryue membres at the age of .xv. yere / he ſhall be hardy as a Lyon / and amyable of forme many facultes ſhal be gy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen hym / he ſhal be a great goer in vyſitynge dyuers countres for to knowe the cuſtomes &amp; ſtatutes of Cyties / &amp; ſhall haue victory ouer all his enemyes / they may nat hynder hym in no maner wyſe / he ſhall haue money by his wyfe / and ſhall ſuffer dyuers doloures of the ſtomacke: he ſhal be mery &amp; loue the company of mery folke. In his ryght ſholder ſhall be a ſygne / by ſwete wordes &amp; adulacions he ſhal be deceyued / he wyll often ſaye one &amp; do ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther / he ſhall haue a wounde with yron / he ſhal be bytten of a dog or of ſome other beeſt / he ſhal be in doubte and haue dyuers enemyes at the age of .xxxiii. yere / and if he eſcape / he ſhall lyue .lxxxiiii. yere after nature.</p>
                  <p>THe woman that ſhall be borne in this tyme ſhal be amyable and fayre / and ſhall nat be longe with her firſte huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bande: and after ſhe ſhal enioye with another by her good and true ſeruyce / ſhe ſhal haue ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>noure and victorye of her enemyes / ſhe ſhall ſuffer payne in the ſtomacke / ſhe ſhal be wy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe &amp; haue woundes in her ſholdres / ſhe ought
<pb facs="tcp:15753:60"/> to fere her latter dayes / whiche ſhal be doubte full by venym / and ſhe ſhal lyue .lxx. yere af<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter nature. The dayes of Mars and Saturne to them ben ryght agreable / and the dayes of Iupiter to them ben co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary: they ſhal be ſwe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te of wordes &amp; pryckynge with theyr tayles / &amp; they wyll murmure detractynge other: and ſay otherwyſe than they wolde be ſayd by.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="Sagittarius" type="zodiac_sign">
                  <head>¶ Of the ſygne of Sagittarius. Good to let blode.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>E it knowen that he which is born vnder Sagittarius from mydde Nouembre / to mydde Decembre ſhal haue mercy of euery man / that whiche he ſeeth he ſhall ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne &amp; haue by reuelacyon / he ſhall go ferre to deſerte places vnknowen &amp; daungerous / &amp; ſhall retourne with great gaynes: he ſhal ſe his fortune encreaſe from day to day / he wyll nat hyde that he hath / he ſhall haue ſome ſyg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes in his handes or fete
/ he ſhall be ferefull / and at .xxii. yere of his age he ſhall haue ſome great peryll / he ſhall paſſe the ſee to his lucre / and he ſhall lyue .lxx vii. yere / and .viii. mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nethes after nature.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:15753:61"/> THe woman that is borne in this tyme ſhall loue to laboure: ſhe ſhall haue dy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uers thoughtꝭ for ſtrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge ſtryues / and may nat ſe one wepe / ſhe ſhall haue victory ouer her enemyes / ſhe ſhall ſpende moche ſyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer by euyll company / ſhe ſhall ſuffer many euylles / ſhe ſhall take great payne to the ende that ſhe maye haue the goodes of her kynneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men. She ought to be maryed at .xiii. yere / &amp; ſhe ſhall haue payne in her iyen at .xiiii. yere / &amp; ſhal haue by enuye at
.xviii. yere ioye / ſhe ſhal ſuffer dolour by enuye: &amp; ſhal be ſeparat from ioye / and ſhall lyue .lxxii. yere after nature. The dayes of Venus &amp; Luna ben right good &amp; the dayes of Mars and Saturne ben euyll: And as well the man as the woman ſhal be inconſtaunt &amp; vnſtable in dedes / they ſhal be of good co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcyence &amp; mercyfull / better to ſtrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gers than to them ſelfe / &amp; they wyll loue god.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="Capricorn" type="zodiac_sign">
                  <head>¶ Of the ſygne of Capricornus. Euyll to let blode.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>E the whiche is borne vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Capricornus from myd Decembre to myd Ianyue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re ſhal be yracundyus / a for nycatour / a lyer: &amp; ſhal be alwayes labouryn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge
<pb facs="tcp:15753:61"/> / and ſhal be noryſſhed with ſtrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges / he ſhall haue many crymes &amp; noyſes / he ſhal be a gouernoure of beeſtes with .iiii. fete / he ſhall nat be longe with his wyfe / he ſhall ſuffre moche ſorowe &amp; heuynes in his youth / he ſhall leue many goodes and rycheſſes / he ſhall haue great peryll at
.xvi. yere / he ſhal be of great courage / he ſhall haunte honeſt peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
/ and ſhal be ryche by women / and ſhal be a conductoure of maydens / his dredren wyll make dyuers eſpyenges vpon hym / &amp; he ſhal lyue .lxx. yere
/ &amp; .iiii. monethes after nature.</p>
                  <p>AS for the woman that is borne in this tyme ſhal be honeſt &amp; ferefull / ſhe ſhall ſurmounte her enemyes / and haue chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of
.iii. men: ſhe wyll go many pylgryma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges in her youth / and after haue great wytte: ſhe ſhall haue great goodes / and ſhe ſhal haue great payne in her iyen / and ſhe ſhal be in her beſte eſtate at .xxx. yere / and ſhall lyue .lxx. yere and .iiii. monethes after nature. The day<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>es of Saturne and of Mars to them be good &amp; the dayes of Sol ben contrary. And bothe the man and the woman ſhall be reſonable / and yet ſhal be enuyous.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="Aquarius" type="zodiac_sign">
                  <head>¶ Of the ſygne of Aquarius. Indifferent to let blode.</head>
                  <p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:15753:62"/> 
                     <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>E that is borne vnder the ſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gne of Aquarius from myd Ianuary vnto myd Februa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry ſhal be louely and yrefull: he wyll nat byleue in vayne thynges / he ſhall haue ſyluer at .xxiiii. yere he ſhal be in eſtate / he ſhal wyn where he gothe / or he ſhal be ſore ſycke
/ &amp; ſhal be hurte with yron / &amp; he ſhall haue fere on the water / and afterwarde ſhall haue good for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune / &amp; ſhall go in to dyuers countrees.</p>
                  <p>THe woman that is borne in this tyme ſhal be delycious: &amp; haue noyſes for her children / ſhe ſhall be in great peryll / at the age of .xxiiii. yere ſhe ſhal be in felycite: ſhe ſhall haue domage by beeſtes with .iiii. fete / ſhe ſhall lyue .lxxvii. yere after nature. The dayes of Venus &amp; of Luna ben right good for them / the dayes of Mars &amp; Saturne ben con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary / &amp; bothe the man &amp; the woman ſhal be reaſonable / &amp; they ſhal nat be ouer ryche.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="Pisces" type="zodiac_sign">
                  <head>¶ Of the ſygne of Piſces. Indifferent to let blode.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He man that is borne vnder the ſygne of Piſces / from mydde Fe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bruary to mydde Marche ſhal be a great goet / a fornycatoure / a mocker / &amp; ſhal
<pb facs="tcp:15753:62"/> be couetous / he wyll ſay one and do another: he ſhall fynde money / he wyll truſte in his ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pyence and ſhal haue good fortune / he ſhal be a defender of Orphelyns and wydowes / he ſhal be ferefull on the water / &amp; he ſhall ſoone paſſe all his aduerſytes
/ &amp; ſhall lyue .lxxiii. yere / and .v. monethes after nature.</p>
                  <p>THe woman that is borne in this tyme ſhal be delycyous / famylyer in geſtes / pleaſaunt of courage / feruent / &amp; ſhall haue ſyckenes in her iyen / and ſhal be ſorow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full by ſhame. Her huſbande wyll leue her / &amp; ſhe ſhall haue moche payne with ſtraungers: ſhe ſhall nat haue her owne / &amp; ſhe ſhall haue payne in her ſtomacke / ſhe ſhall lyue .lxxvii. after nature. The dayes of Mercury / Iupiter and Venus ben right good for them / and the dayes of Mars and Saturne to them ben con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trary / and bothe the man &amp; the woman ſhall lyue faythfully.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="43" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ Thus endeth the .xii. Sygnes of deſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyes of man and woman born vnder them. And here after foloweth the Scyence of Phyzonomye / for to knowe the naturall inclyna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyon of man and woman.</head>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:15753:63"/> 
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>O as Pholomeus ſaythe Phyzonomye of the whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che hath ben ſpoken of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore: is a ſcience that Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nomyers haue for to kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we the naturall inclyna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyon of man and woman good or euyll: by dyuers ſygnes on them in be holdynge them oonly. The whiche inclyna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyon / we ought to folowe if it be good. But if it be euyl by vertue and ſtrength of vnder<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtandynge / we ought to eſchewe and euyte it as to the effecte / &amp; to withſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de the ſayd euyll inclynacyons. Aſtronomyers vſe this ſcyen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce none other wyſe. The prudent / vertuous &amp; wyſe men may be as touchyng theyr maners All other than theyr ſygnes demonſtreth and ſheweth in their reygne. For theſe tokens that do ſygnyfye vyce is nat ſeen in a wyſe man thoughe the ſygne be ſo / as an ale ſtake / or a ſygne hanged before an houſe / in the whiche often tymes is noo drynke. ¶ For howe be it that a man by his wyſdom and vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge folowe nat the euyll influences of the celeſtyall bodyes that ben vpon hym / and yet corrupteth nat the ſygnes and demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cions of the ſayd influences / but thoſe ſygnes naturally haue ſygnory and domynacion on
<pb facs="tcp:15753:63"/> them / in the whiche they be for to haue natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally that whiche they ſygnyfy / thoughe that a man folowe them / or folowe them nat.</p>
               <p>¶ wherfore Aſtronomyers ſay that the moſt parte of men and women folowe theyr natu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rall inclynacions to vyce or vertue / for that the moſt parte of them be nat wyſe &amp; prudent as they oughte to be / and they vſe no vertue of theyr owne myndes / but enſueth theyr ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſualyte. And by theſe celeſtyall influences of the whiche is ſhewed by ſygnes outwarde of ſuche ſygnes is the ſayd ſcyence of Phyzono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mye knowen. For the whiche it behoueth fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſte to knowe that the yere is deuyded in .iiii. partyes (as it hathe ben ſayd before) that is to wyt Pryme tyme / Some / Herueſt / &amp; wyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter / that ben compared to the .iiii. Elementes. Pryme tyme to the ayre. Somer to the fyre. Herueſt to the erthe. And wynter to the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. Of the whiche .iiii. Elementes euery man and woman is formed and made / and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the whiche none may lyue. The fyre is ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te and drye. The ayre is hote and moyſt. The water is moyſte and colde. The erthe is colde and drye. Alſo they ſaye that the perſone on whom the fyre reygneth is Coleryke of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleccion (that is to ſaye) hote and drye. He on whom the ayre reygneth is Sanguyne of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pleccyon
<pb facs="tcp:15753:64"/> (that is to ſaye) hote and moyſte. He on whom the water domyneth is Flumaty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke of compleccyon (that is to ſay) moyſte and colde. He on whom the erthe domyneth is Me<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lancolyke of compleccion (that is to ſay) colde &amp; drye. The whiche compleccions they know<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lege and deſerue the one from the other.</p>
               <p>AS the Coleryke hath nature of fyre ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te and drye / natually is lene and ſklen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der / couetous / yrefull / haſty / braynles / folyſſhe / malycyous / deceytfull / and ſubtyll / where he beſtoweth his wyt. He hath wyne of the Lyon (that is to ſaye) whan he is dron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken he chydeth / fyghteth
/ and comonly he lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth to be clad in blacke / as ruſſet / &amp; graye.</p>
               <p>¶ The Sanguyne hath nature of Ayre hote and moyſte / and is large / plentuous / attem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pred / amyable / abundaunte in nature / mery / ſyngynge laughynge / lykynge / ruddy &amp; gra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyous. He hath his wyne of the Ape / the more he drynketh the meryer he is: &amp; draweth to wo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>men / &amp; naturally loueth hye coloured cloth.</p>
               <p>¶ The Flumatyke hath nature of water / col<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de and moyſte
/ he is heuy / ſlowe / ſlepy / inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyous / comonly he ſpytteth whan he is mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued &amp; hath his wyne of the Shepe / for whan he is dronken he accompteth hym ſelfe wyſeſt and be loueth moſte and aboue all coloures
/
<pb facs="tcp:15753:64"/> the coloure of grene clothe.</p>
               <p>¶ The Melancolyke hathe nature of Erthe / colde and drye / he is heuy / couetous / bacbyter malycyous / and ſlowe. His wyne is of the hogge / for whan he is dronken he deſyreth ſle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe / and to lye downe and haue his reſte / and he loueth the coloure of blacke beſte.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="44" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ Here foloweth the Iugementes of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes body. Capitulo
.xliiii.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Or to come to our purpoſe of ſpekynge of vyſyble ſyg<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes / we wyll begyn to ſpe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke of the ſygnes of the hed. Fyrſte we warne you that you ought to beware of all perſones that haue defaute of membres natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally / as of fote hande iye / or other membre / &amp; thoughe that he be but a creple / and ſpecyally of a man that hath no berde / for ſuche ben in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clyned to dyuers vyces and euylles / and one oughte to eſchewe his company / as his mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall enemy. Alſo Ptholomeus ſayth that mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che and playne heer ſygnyfyeth a perſone py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous &amp; debonayre. They that haue reed heer / ben comonly yrefull and lacke wytte / &amp; ben of lytell trouthe. Bblacke heer / good vyſage / 
<pb facs="tcp:15753:65"/> and good coloure / ſygnyfyeth very loue of Iuſtyce. Harde heer ſygnyfyeth that the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſone loueth peas and concorde: and is of good and ſubtyll wytte. A man that hathe blacke heer and red berde / ſygnyfyeth to be lecherous vniuſt / and a vaunter: and one ought nat to truſte in hym. The yelowe heer and cryſpe ſy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gnyfyeth man laughynge / mery / lecherous / &amp; deceytefull. Blacke heer &amp; cryſpe ſygnyfyeth melancolyke / ſechery / euyll thought / and ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry lyberall. Hangynge heer ſygnyfyeth wyt / with malyce. Great plente of heer in a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man ſygnyfyeth boyſtouſnes and couetyſe. A perſone with great iyes is ſlouthfull / vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamefaſt / inobedyent / &amp; weneth to knowe moche more than he dothe / but whan the iyen ben full meane nat to bygge nor to ſmal / and that they be nat to blacke nor to grene / ſuche a man is of great vnderſtandynge / curteyſe / faythfull and truſty. A perſone that is blere iyed / gogle iyed / and ſquynt iyed ſygnyfyeth malyce / vengeaunce / cautele / and treaſon.</p>
               <p>They that haue great wyde iyen &amp; haue lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge heer on theyr browes and iye lyddes ſygny<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fyeth folyſſhenes / harde of vnderſtandynge: and ben euyll by nature. The perſones whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che haue theyr iyen mouynge faſte from one ſyde to another / and haue theyr ſyghte ſharpe
<pb facs="tcp:15753:65"/> and quycke ſygnyfyeth fraude / &amp; thefte / and is of lytell truſte. The iyen that ben blacke / clere / &amp; ſhynynge ben the beſte / &amp; the moſte cer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tayne and they ſygnyfye wyt and diſcrecion / and ſuche a perſone is worthy to be loued: for he is full of truthe / and of good condycions. The iyen that ben ardaunt and ſperkelynge: ſygnyfye ſtronge herte / force / and puyſaunce. The iyen that ben whytyſſhe and fleſſhely / ſygnyfye a perſone enclyned to vyce / lechery and full of fraude. Aſtronomyers ſaye that whan a perſone beholdeth often as abaſſhed ſhamefaſte / &amp; ferefull / and that in beholdyng it ſemeth that he ſyngeth / and he hathe ſmall droppes apperyng in his iyen: than it is for cer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tayne that ſuche perſones loue and deſyre the welth of them that they beholde. But whan any loketh in caſtynge his iyen aſyde / as by wantonneſſe / ſuche perſones ben deceytfull / and purchaſe to greue hym / &amp; ſuche perſones wyll diſhonoure women / and they ought to be taken hede of / for ſuche lokes ben falſe / le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherous
/ &amp; deceyuable. They that haue ſmall garyſſhe iyen and ſharpe ſygnyfye a perſone melancolyous / hardy / an euyl ſayer / &amp; cruell. And if a lytel vayne appere bytwene the iye and the noſe of a wenche / they ſay that it ſyg<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nyfyeth virgynyte / and in a man ſubtylyte
<pb facs="tcp:15753:66"/> of vnderſtandynge / and if it appere great &amp; blacke / it ſygnyfyeth corrupcion / hete / and melancoly in a woman / and in a man rudenes &amp; defaute of wytte / but that vayne apperyth nat alwayes. But the iyen that ben yelowe and haue no heeres on the browee ſygnyfieth meſelry and euyll diſpoſicion of body. Great heeres and longe ſignyfyeth rudeneſſe / harde wytte / and lechery. The beteled browes ſyg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyfyeth malyce / cruelte / lecherye / and enuye. And whan the browes ben thynne / it ſygny<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fyeth ſubtyll engyne / wyt / and faythfulnes. Holowe iyen and hangynge browes ſygny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyeth a perſone full of euyll ſayinge / of euyll thought / a great drynker: and comonly ſetteth his mynde to malyce. A lytell ſhorte vyſage and a ſmall necke / and a lytell ſklender noſe ſygnyfyeth a perſone of great herte / haſtye &amp; yrefull. A longe noſe and hye by nature ſyg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyfyeth prowes and hardynes. A ſhorte rey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed noſe ſygnyfyeth haſtynes / lechery / hardy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes / and an vndertaker. A hauked noſe that boweth to the vpper lyppe ſygnyfyeth maly<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce
/ deceyte vntruth and lechery. A great noſe &amp; hye in the myddes ſygnyfyeth a wyſe man and well ſpoken. A great noſe with wyde noſe thrylles ſygnyfyeth glotony &amp; yre. A red face &amp; ſhorte ſygnyfyeth a perſone full of ryot
<pb facs="tcp:15753:66"/> debate / &amp; vnfaythfull. A vyſage nouther to ſhorte nor to longe / and that is nat ouer fatte with good coloure betokeneth a man veryta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble / amyable / wyſe / wytty / ſeruyable / debo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nayre / &amp; well o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dred in all his workes. A fat vyſage &amp; full of rude fleſſhe ſygnyfyeth glo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tony / neclygence / rudenes of wyt and vnder<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtandyng. A ſklender face &amp; ſomwhat longe ſygnyfyeth a perſone well aduyſed in all his workes by good meaſure. A lytell ſho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>te vy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage of yelowe coloure ſygnyfyeth a perſone deceyuynge / vntrue / malycyous / and full of harme. A vyſage longe and fayre ſygnyfieth a man hote / vniuſt / ſpytefull / and full of yre &amp; cruelte. They that haue their mouthes great and wyde ſygnyfieth yre &amp; hardynes. A lytel mouthe ſygnyfyeth melancoly / heuynes / har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de wytte / &amp; euyll thought. He that hath great lyppes hath a token of rudenes / and defaute of wytte. Thynne lyppes ſygnyfyeth lycke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſnes &amp; leſynges. Tethe euen ſette &amp; thyn / betoketh a true louer / lecherous / and of good compleccion. Longe tethe &amp; great ſygnyfyeth haſtynes and yre. Longe eeres ſygnyfyeth fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye / but it is a ſygne of good memory. Lytell eeres ſygnyfyeth lechery and thefte. A perſon that hathe a good voyce well ſownynge / is hardy / wyſe / &amp; well ſpoken. A meane voyce
<pb facs="tcp:15753:67"/> that is nat to ſmall nor to great / ſygnyfyeth wytte purueyaunce / truthe &amp; ryghtwyſenes. A man that ſpeketh haſtely to be ſette by. A great voyce in a woman is an euyll ſygne. A ſofte voyce ſygnyfyeth a perſon full of en<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uye / of ſuſpeccion &amp; leſynges. And ouer ſmal voyce ſygnyfyeth great herte &amp; folye. Great voyce ſygnyfeth haſtynes &amp; yre. A man that ſtyreth alway whan he ſpeketh &amp; chaungeth voyce is enuyous / nyce / dronken / and euyll condycyoned. A perſone that ſpeketh attem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poratly without mouynge is of perfyte vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandynge / of good condycyon / &amp; of good counceyle. A man with a browne vyſage / reuynge ieyn: &amp; yelowe tethe is of lytell truth a traytour / &amp; hath ſtynkynge brethe. A perſon with a longe ſkender necke is cruel / without pyte / haſty / and brayneles. A perſone with a ſhorte necke is full of fraude / ſtryfe / decepcion and malyce. A perſone that hath a very lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge thycke necke ſygnyfyeth glotonye / force &amp; great lechery. A manly woman that is great and rudely membred is by nature melancoly<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ous / varyaunte / &amp; lecherous. A perſone that hath a great lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge bely ſygnyfyeth ſmall wyt pryde / and lechery. A lytell bely &amp; large fete / ſygnyfyeth good vnderſtandynge / good cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceyle and true. A perſone hauynge large fete / 
<pb facs="tcp:15753:67"/> hye &amp; bowynge ſholdres ſygnyfyeth prowes hardynes / haſtynes / truthe and wytte. Shol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dres ſharpe &amp; longe betokeneth trechery / vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truthe / ſtryuyng / and vnnaturall. whan the armes ben ſo longe that they maye ſtretche to the ioynte of the kne / it is a token of prowes / lyberalyte / truthe / honoure / good wytte / and vnderſtandynge. whan the armes ben ſhorte it is a ſygne of ygnoraunce / of euyll nature / and a perſone that loueth debate. Longe han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des and ſklender fyngers ſygnyfyeth ſubtyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te / and a perſone that hathe deſyre to knowe dyuers thyngꝭ. Small handes &amp; ſhorte thycke fyngers betokeneth foly / and lyghtnes of cou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rage. Thycke large and bygge handes ſygny<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fyeth force / haſtynes / hardynes / and wytte. Clere and ſhynynge nayles of good coloure ſygnyfyeth wytte and encreaſe of honoure. Nayles full of whyte ſpottes and reueled ſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnyfyeth a perſone auarycyous
/ lecherous / proude / of herte / full of wytte and malyce. The fote thycke &amp; full of fleſſhe ſygnyfyeth a perſone outragyous / vygoryous / and of ly<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tell wytte. Small fete and lyght ſygnyfyeth hardynes of vnderſtandynge / &amp; lytell truthe Fete flatte and ſhorte ſygnyfyeth an anguyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhous perſone / of ſmall wyſdom and vncur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teyſe. A ꝑſone that gothe a great paſe is great
<pb facs="tcp:15753:68"/> of herte and diſpyteful / and ſygnyfyeth well to proſpere in all thyngꝭ. A perſone that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth ſmall ſteppes and thycke is ſuſpecyous / full of enuye / and euyll wyll. A perſone that hath a ſmal flatte fote and caſteth as a childe ſygnyfyeth hardynes &amp; wytte / but the ſayde perſone hath dyuers thoughtꝭ. A perſone that hathe ſofte fleſſhe nat to colde nor to hote ſyg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyfyeth a well diſpoſed perſone / of good vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>derſtandynge &amp; ſubtyll wytte / full of truthe and encreaſynge of honoure. A perſone that laugheth gladly and hath grene iyen is debo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nayre of good wytte / true / wyſe &amp; lecherous. A perſone that laugheth fayntly is ſlouthful melancolyous / ſuſpecious / malycyous / &amp; ſub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyll. ¶ Aſtronomyers ſaye for that there ben dyuers ſygnes in a man and woman / &amp; that they ben ſomtyme contrary one to the other / one oughte to Iuge moſte comonly after the ſygnes in the vyſage. And firſte to the iyen for they ben moſte true &amp; prouable. And they ſay alſo that god formed no creature for to en habyte the worlde wyſer than man / for there is no condycion nor maner in a beeſt: but that it is fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de comprehended in man. Naturally a man is hardy / as the Lyon. Prue and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy / as the Oxe. Large and lyberall / as the Cocke. Auarycyous / as the Dogge. Harde &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:15753:68"/> ſwyfte / as the Harte. Debonayre and true: as the turtle Douue. Malycyous / as the Leopar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de. Pryue &amp; tame / as the Douue. Dolorous &amp; gylefull / as the Foxe. Symple and mylde / as the Lame. Shrewde
/ as the Ape. Lyghte / as the Horſe. Softe and pyteable / as the beer. Dere &amp; precyous / as the Olyphaunte. Good and holſome / as the Vnycorne. Vyle &amp; ſlouth full / as the Aſſe. Fayre &amp; proude / as the Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cocke. Glotonous / as the wolfe. Enuyous / as the Bytche. Rebell and inobedyent / as the Nyghtyngale. Humble / as the Pegyon. Fell and folyſſhe / as the Ouſtryche. Profytable / as the Pyſmyre. Dyſſolute &amp; vagabounde / as the Gote. Spytefull / as the Feſau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. Sof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te and meke / as the Checkyn. Mouable &amp; va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryinge / as the Fyſſhe. Lecherous / as the Bore Stronge &amp; puyſſaunt / as the Camell. Tray<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>toure / as the Mule. Aduyſed / as the Mouſe. Reſonable / as an Aungell. And therfore he is called the lytell worlde: or ellys he is called all creatures / for he taketh parte of all.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>¶ Finis.</trailer>
            <trailer>¶ Thus endeth the Compoſt of Ptho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomeus Prynce of Aſtronomye.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <pb facs="tcp:15753:69"/>
            <head>¶ Imprynted by me Robert wyer / Dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynge at the ſygne of ſeynt Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelyſte / in ſeynt Martyns Paryſſhe in the Felde
/ in the byſſhop of Nor wyt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che rentes / beſyde Charyng croſſe.</head>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>ROBERT: WYRE·</head>
                  <figDesc>printer's device of Robert Wyer (or Wyre)</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:15753:69"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
